<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Four sermons preached upon solemne occasions I. The troubler of Israel. II. The righteous mans concern for the churches misery. Preached before the judges. III. Cæsars due honour, preached before the mayor and aldermen of Leicester, May 29. 1669. IV. Davids work and rest, preached before the election of the mayor. By Tho. Stanhope A.M. Vicar of St. Margarets in Leicester.</title>
            <author>Stanhope, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5233B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221868</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833115</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833115</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37590</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61282)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37590)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2063:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Four sermons preached upon solemne occasions I. The troubler of Israel. II. The righteous mans concern for the churches misery. Preached before the judges. III. Cæsars due honour, preached before the mayor and aldermen of Leicester, May 29. 1669. IV. Davids work and rest, preached before the election of the mayor. By Tho. Stanhope A.M. Vicar of St. Margarets in Leicester.</title>
                  <author>Stanhope, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 90, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Henry Brome, at the Gun, at the west end of St. Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Preached ... judges" preceded by a left curly bracket.</note>
                  <note>With an initial imprimatur leaf.</note>
                  <note>With marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Each sermon has a divisional title page.</note>
                  <note>With a final leaf of errata.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37590:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FOUR SERMONS Preached upon Solemne Occaſions.
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>The Troubler of Iſrael.</hi> Preached before the Judges.</item>
                  <item>II. <hi>The Righteous Mans Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for the Churches Miſery.</hi> Preached before the Judges.</item>
                  <item>III. Caeſars <hi>due Honour, Preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Mayor and Aldermen of</hi> Leiceſter, May 29. 1669.</item>
                  <item>IV. Davids <hi>Work and Reſt, Preached before the Election of the Mayor.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Tho. Stanhope A. M.</hi> Vicar of St. <hi>Margarets</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Brome,</hi> at the Gun, at the Weſt End of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:37590:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur, </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Rob. Grove</hi> R. P. Dom. Epiſc. <hi>Lond.</hi> a Sac. Dom.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37590:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:37590:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37590:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Reverend Father in God, WILLIAM Lord Biſhop of LINCOLNE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe Sermons now pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, do (pardon the expreſſion) <hi>challenge</hi> your Lordſhips Name to be praefixed before them, as yours in point of <hi>Right.</hi> They were
<pb facs="tcp:37590:4"/>preached in your Dioceſe, where I now reſide; and are the <hi>Firſt-Fruits</hi> of my poor Labours expoſed to the World, and upon that ſcore, ought to be <hi>offered</hi> into your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Hands. It is not a curious <hi>Itch</hi> of Popular Applauſe which hath drawn me into Print, (I could never fancy any thing of mine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved any Perſons notice.) Nor will I alleadge the <hi>Importunity of Friends</hi> as a Ground of this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking; (though ſometimes ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſollicited.) But to ſay <hi>truth,</hi> The Auditors were ſo ingenuous as favourably to accept them when Preached, which makes me hope they may be ſerviceable from the Preſs, as they ſeemed to be from
<pb facs="tcp:37590:4"/>the Pulpit. Such as they are, I humbly preſent them to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as a real Teſtimony how much I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt faithful Servant,</hi> Tho. Stanhope.</signed>
               <dateline>Leiceſter <date>Novem. <hi>9. 1669.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:37590:5"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:37590:5"/>
                  <p>THE TROUBLER OF ISRAEL: A SERMON Preached before the Judges at St. <hi>Maries</hi> Church in <hi>Leice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, March,</hi> 18. 1668/9.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Tho. Stanhope A. M.</hi> Vicar of St. <hi>Margarets</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:37590:6"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37590:6"/>
                  <head>The Troubler of <hi>ISRAEL.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 Chronicles. 2.7.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Achar</hi> the troubler of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed in the thing accurſed.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Reuben</hi> by default, <hi>forfeited</hi> the right of <hi>firſt-born,</hi> that <hi>priviledge</hi> was <hi>ſhared</hi> between <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſeph</hi> and <hi>Judah.
<note place="margin">Gen. 48.22. Gen. 49.8.</note> Joſeph</hi> had the <hi>double portion, Judah</hi> the <hi>dominion over his Brethren</hi> for <hi>the Scepter was not to depart from him, nor a Law-giver from between his feet, until</hi> Shiloh <hi>came.</hi> His <hi>Tribe</hi> therefore hath the <hi>firſt place</hi> among the <hi>twelve,</hi> where the Iſraelitiſh <hi>pedigree</hi> is drawn down from <hi>Adam,</hi> to the times of <hi>Ezra;</hi> who (if not the <hi>Author</hi> of) may well be conceived an <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional ſupplier</hi> to this <hi>Book.</hi> Three Sons he had by <hi>Shuah,</hi> but his Family <hi>multiplied</hi> moſt by <hi>Pharez</hi> and <hi>Zarah,</hi> begotten upon <hi>Tamar,</hi> one of the <hi>four wicked women,</hi> mentioned by St. <hi>Matthew</hi> in our Saviours <hi>Genealogy;</hi> to ſhew that <hi>deſcending from, he came to ſave ſinners.</hi> And the <hi>Progeny</hi> of theſe is ſlightly <hi>paſſed</hi> over with a bare <hi>naming,</hi> till <hi>Achar</hi> comes in <hi>play;</hi> whoſe <hi>life</hi> being more <hi>notorious,</hi> his <hi>Character</hi> is delivered
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37590:7"/>more at <hi>large. Achar, the troubler of Iſrael, who tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed in the thing accurſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the <hi>Judge</hi> be ſet upon the <hi>Bench,</hi> 'tis no marvel to ſee a <hi>Priſoner</hi> at the <hi>Bar.</hi> You <hi>(my Lords)</hi> appear by this <hi>ſolemnity,</hi> ready to ſit upon your <hi>Judgement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeat;</hi> my <hi>Text</hi> preſents a <hi>Malefactor</hi> to be <hi>tried,</hi> and <hi>draws an Indictment</hi> againſt <hi>him:</hi> wherein after the <hi>uſual form,</hi> you may pleaſe to obſerve, 1. <hi>His Name,</hi> 2. <hi>His Crime. His Name</hi> Achar. <hi>His Crime</hi> declared <hi>more generally, more particularly. More generally;</hi> He was <hi>the troubler of Iſrael: More particularly;</hi> He <hi>tranſgreſſed in the thing accurſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">I. <hi>His Name. Achar,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Text; Achan,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Joſhua.</hi> An <hi>eaſie alteration</hi> by only <hi>chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the <hi>laſt Letter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joſh. 7.1.</note> to <hi>expreſs</hi> the <hi>evil</hi> enſuing upon his <hi>Wickedneſs,</hi> Nabal <hi>is his Name, and folly is with him,</hi> ſo the Scripture of that <hi>fottiſh dolt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.25.</note> Achar <hi>is his name and trouble comes by him.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Gods Spirit</hi> loves ſometimes to be <hi>Rhetorical.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,
<note place="margin">Rom. i. 29.-31.</note> within 3 verſes together. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Gilgal <hi>ſhall go into Captivity,</hi> Amos 5.5. Once more out of either <hi>Teſtament. Fear, the pit and the ſnare are upon thee,</hi> Iſai. 24.18. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Not to think of himſelf more highly than he ought to think, but to think ſoberly.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.3. With ſeveral ſuch <hi>Paranomaſia's.</hi> Nor are we <hi>Miniſters</hi> always <hi>blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy,</hi> if <hi>ſcattering</hi> ſome <hi>Flowers</hi> of <hi>Elegancy</hi> in our <hi>Sermons. Diſcourſes</hi> from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> may as well be <hi>nauſeous</hi> when <hi>ſlovenly worded,</hi> as when <hi>ſtarchedly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</hi> All men have not the Gift of <hi>neat Elocution;</hi> where God hath <hi>beſtowed it,</hi> why may it not be <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed</hi> to <hi>take</hi> mens <hi>ears</hi> for the <hi>gaining</hi> their <hi>ſouls?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to leave this <hi>Criticiſme.</hi> The <hi>Perſon</hi> was <hi>Achar,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37590:7"/>Great-granchild</hi> to the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Judah,
<note place="margin">Gen. 32.28.</note> deſcended</hi> from <hi>Jacob,</hi> who <hi>as a Prince had power with God, and with men and prevailed. Piety</hi> we ſee, is not <hi>hereditary.</hi> Men may <hi>bequeath Lands,</hi> and <hi>Houſes,</hi> and <hi>Goods;</hi> but they cannot draw a <hi>Conveyance</hi> of <hi>Grace.</hi> We may from our <hi>Parents</hi> derive the <hi>Features</hi> of their <hi>Faces,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tertull. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog. cap.</hi> 18.</note> not the <hi>Endowments</hi> of their <hi>Souls. Fiunt Chriſtiani non naſcuntur.</hi> For being <hi>men,</hi> we thank our <hi>fathers</hi> on <hi>earth,</hi> for being <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> we thank our <hi>Father</hi> in <hi>Heaven.</hi> Who knows not that <hi>faithful Abraham</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat a <hi>ſcoffing Iſmael?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 13.22.</note> that from <hi>Holy Iſaac</hi> proceeded a <hi>prophane Eſau?</hi> David, <hi>the man after Gods own heart,</hi> ſaw among his Children a <hi>rebellious Abſalom,</hi> and an <hi>aſpiring Adonijah.</hi> Yea, <hi>Elies Sons</hi> (though he a <hi>religious Prieſt</hi>) were <hi>ſons of Belial,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.12.17.</note> and through their <hi>ſin, men abhorred the offering of the Lord.</hi> Look among the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Judah,</hi> at an <hi>exact checker-work</hi> in <hi>four</hi> immediate <hi>Succeſſions. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> is <hi>followed</hi> with a <hi>good Jotham,</hi> that <hi>Jotham</hi> with a <hi>wicked Ahaz,</hi> that <hi>Ahaz</hi> with a <hi>pious Hezekiah,</hi> that <hi>Hezekiah</hi> with a <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Manaſſeh.</hi> So <hi>free</hi> are the <hi>diſpenſations</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> without <hi>confinement</hi> to <hi>places</hi> or <hi>families.</hi> Our <hi>vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Progenitors</hi> could not <hi>entail Holineſs</hi> upon their <hi>Poſterity. All are not Iſrael, that are of Iſrael: neither.
<note place="margin">Rom. 9.6.7:</note> becauſe they are the ſeed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>are they all children.</hi> As <hi>Jeroboams wicked houſe</hi> may yield <hi>one</hi> in whom <hi>is found ſome good thing towards God:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Kings 14.13.</note> ſo from the <hi>root</hi> of <hi>Jacob,</hi> may grow ſuch a <hi>luxuriant putrified branch,</hi> as this <hi>Perſon</hi> in the Text, Achar, <hi>the troubler of</hi> Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>But as he derived his <hi>pedigree</hi> from <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſo from the <hi>firſt houſe</hi> of his <hi>race,</hi> the <hi>eminenteſt</hi> of the <hi>Tribes,</hi> that of <hi>Judah.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 49.8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> On whom <hi>Father Iſrael</hi> beſtowed the <hi>ruling-power,</hi> as his <hi>death-bed Legacy: thy Fathers children ſhall bow down unto thee.</hi> A <hi>Tribe appointed</hi> by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37590:8"/>God as <hi>Captain</hi> over the reſt in the <hi>Canaanitiſh War.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Judg. 1.2.</note> A <hi>Tribe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 7.14.</note> out of which came his <hi>choſen King David,</hi> and afterwards <hi>the ſon of</hi> David, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</hi> Hereby <hi>ennobled</hi> above them all, like the <hi>Lyon</hi> (its <hi>enſign</hi> of <hi>honour</hi>) above the <hi>beaſts</hi> of the <hi>field. Great men</hi> are not always <hi>good,</hi> nor can the <hi>beſt extraction</hi> warrant the <hi>beſt condition.</hi> Eſpecially of <hi>late, ſinning</hi> is become a <hi>piece of gallantry,</hi> and our <hi>Age</hi> hath brought it into a great deal of <hi>credit. Formerly</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the <hi>ſon of a King</hi> might <hi>rebel</hi> againſt his <hi>father;</hi> now he is a <hi>puiſny in wickedneſs</hi> that dares not <hi>draw ſword</hi> againſt his <hi>Soveraign.</hi> In <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>time</hi> a <hi>Korah</hi> would <hi>engage</hi> againſt <hi>King and Prieſt;</hi> but the <hi>rable</hi> in <hi>our days</hi> have learnt to <hi>hector</hi> out both <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Prelate,</hi> and <hi>force</hi> them to <hi>compliance</hi> by <hi>ſeditious tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults. They that are drunk are drunk in the night,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> 1 Theſſal. 5.7. Now 'tis <hi>gentile</hi> to <hi>ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> at the <hi>Mid-day Sun,</hi> and he is a <hi>bungler</hi> in his <hi>art</hi> that is <hi>ſober</hi> at <hi>Noon.</hi> One <hi>Achan</hi> under <hi>Joſhua,</hi> might <hi>plunder</hi> at the <hi>ſiege</hi> of <hi>Jericho:</hi> but he is <hi>no body</hi> with <hi>us,</hi> who <hi>fils</hi> not his <hi>houſe</hi> with <hi>the goods of his brethren;</hi> or <hi>the ſpoyls of the Temple.</hi> I would theſe <hi>faults</hi> were only to be <hi>imputed</hi> to the <hi>meaner ſort;</hi> that perſons of <hi>quality</hi> might <hi>acquit</hi> themſelves from the <hi>leaſt ſuſpition</hi> of being <hi>guilty.</hi> But alas! the very <hi>Tribe</hi> of <hi>Judah</hi> is <hi>corrupt,</hi> the <hi>honour</hi> of our <hi>Nation</hi> is too much <hi>ſtained,</hi> and they that ſhould <hi>defend</hi> their <hi>Nobility,</hi> by <hi>vertue</hi> do frequently <hi>proſtitute</hi> it to the <hi>groſſeſt vices.</hi> Not that I charge this upon <hi>all Gentlemen;</hi> God forbid! We know there are <hi>ſome</hi> whoſe <hi>ſpirits</hi> are more <hi>raiſed:</hi> whoſe <hi>ingenuity ſcorns</hi> to admit a <hi>ſoyle</hi> with, or give <hi>countenance</hi> to any <hi>open wickedneſs.</hi> And (God be bleſſed) this <hi>Countrey</hi> wants not its <hi>ſhare</hi> of ſuch <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent men.</hi> But ſure <hi>impiety</hi> was never ſo <hi>generally fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured</hi>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37590:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>by <hi>Great ones,</hi> nor the <hi>commiſſion of ſin</hi> ſo much in <hi>faſhion</hi> as <hi>now</hi> it is. We are fallen into the <hi>licentious times</hi> of the World. <hi>Quicquid libet, licet.</hi> And when ſo many <hi>Achars</hi> are <hi>abroad,</hi> no marvel if they prove <hi>peſtilential</hi> to the <hi>Kingdome.</hi> Such men carry <hi>trouble</hi> in their <hi>Name,</hi> and the <hi>troublers of the Country</hi> ſhall be their <hi>Character;</hi> Achar <hi>the troubler of Iſrael:</hi> Which leads me from <hi>the Malefacior,</hi> to 2. <hi>His Indictment,</hi> and therein to the <hi>Firſt</hi> Branch of the <hi>Second</hi> General.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>The troubler of Iſrael.</hi> The <hi>Scripture</hi> uſeth not to <hi>complement</hi> with <hi>ſinners.</hi> When the <hi>World</hi> dares not <hi>open</hi> its <hi>mouth,</hi> and a <hi>carnal friend</hi> layes his <hi>finger</hi> on his <hi>lips, Gods word</hi> will <hi>ſpeak plainly.</hi> The <hi>greateſt</hi> ſhall have no <hi>better</hi> than they <hi>deſerve,</hi> and the <hi>meaneſt</hi> ſhall not <hi>want</hi> their <hi>juſt commendation. A charity of two mites</hi> ſhall be <hi>recorded</hi> from a <hi>Widow.</hi> A <hi>box of oyntment</hi> ſhall be <hi>known</hi> through the <hi>World,</hi> if brought by <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> to her <hi>Saviour:</hi> and the <hi>poor Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reptan</hi> ſhall be <hi>regiſtred</hi> in <hi>Gods volumn,</hi> for well <hi>enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining</hi> her <hi>gueſt Elijah.</hi> This may <hi>encourage</hi> us to do <hi>good.</hi> But on the contrary, if we <hi>deviate</hi> from the <hi>pathes</hi> of <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> if we <hi>ſtain</hi> our <hi>ſouls</hi> with <hi>impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> no marvel if our <hi>Names</hi> be <hi>blotted</hi> with <hi>diſgrace. Great ſinners</hi> (though <hi>eminent</hi> in the World) have not <hi>eſcaped</hi> their <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, their <hi>brands</hi> of <hi>infamy:</hi> Witneſs <hi>Ahab,</hi> and <hi>Ahaz,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſeh.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Kings 21.25.</note> The <hi>firſt</hi> is ſaid to <hi>ſell himſelf to do wickedneſs.</hi> The <hi>ſecond</hi> is mentioned in a <hi>ſtrange phraſe: This is that King</hi> Ahaz.
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 28.22. 2 Chron. 33.9.</note> And the <hi>third</hi> could not <hi>readily deſerve</hi> above what he <hi>had: he made</hi> Judah <hi>to do worſe than the Heathen, whom the Lord caſt out before the children of Iſrael.</hi> Adde to theſe, <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> conſtantly <hi>named</hi> with this <hi>ſcurvy addition, who made Iſrael to ſin:</hi> And withal remember what <hi>Achar</hi> is <hi>ſtiled</hi> in the Text, Achar, <hi>the troubler of Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:37590:9"/>
                  <p>Methinks the very <hi>odium</hi> caſt upon <hi>ſinners</hi> ſhould make us <hi>averſe</hi> to the <hi>Commiſſion</hi> of <hi>ſin.</hi> Were it a thing would render us <hi>honourable</hi> in the World, would it <hi>perfume</hi> our <hi>memories</hi> in the <hi>noſtrils</hi> of men, and make them <hi>fragrant</hi> to <hi>future generations;</hi> we might have ſome <hi>encouragement</hi> to <hi>court</hi> and <hi>embrace</hi> it. But quite <hi>otherwiſe:</hi> It layes a <hi>blemiſh</hi> upon our <hi>greateſt glory,</hi> it renders us <hi>deſpicable</hi> in the <hi>eyes</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> it <hi>ſoils</hi> our very <hi>aſhes</hi> in the <hi>grave,</hi> and cauſeth our <hi>names</hi> to <hi>rot</hi> upon the <hi>earth:</hi> enough to <hi>ſtir</hi> up our <hi>hatred</hi> unto, and <hi>reſolutions</hi> againſt <hi>it.</hi> Eſpecially, <hi>You the Worthies</hi> of the <hi>County, Stain</hi> not the <hi>goodneſs of your Birth,</hi> with <hi>the badneſs of your lives. Sin</hi> is <hi>diſcreditable</hi> in <hi>any, moſt</hi> in <hi>Gentlemen.</hi> They were <hi>grievous times</hi> of which <hi>Salvian</hi> complained,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Salvian. de Guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. Dei lib.</hi> 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Volunt ſibi id Majores quaſi privilegium vendicare, ut jure ſuo crimina committant. The Nobles of that Age pleaded a priviledge to act wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, as a piece of State.</hi> May that <hi>ſtrange ſpirit</hi> never <hi>diſturb</hi> our <hi>Generation,</hi> nor make the <hi>leaſt eſſay</hi> upon our <hi>Gentry.</hi> Do you therefore <hi>prop</hi> your <hi>Honourable Title</hi> by <hi>Vertuous Actions,</hi> and <hi>uphold</hi> the <hi>repute</hi> of your <hi>Families</hi> by <hi>exemplary goodneſs.</hi> This will <hi>endear</hi> you to all <hi>ſober perſons:</hi> This will prove a <hi>bleſſing</hi> to your <hi>Countrey,</hi> and <hi>perpetuate</hi> your <hi>fame</hi> beyond <hi>braſs</hi> and <hi>marble;</hi> when the <hi>prophane</hi> and <hi>wicked</hi> ſhall have no better a <hi>remembrance</hi> than <hi>He</hi> in the Text, Achar, <hi>the troubler of Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Troubler of Iſrael.</hi> The <hi>phraſe</hi> relates to a <hi>paſſage</hi> in Joſhua 7 25. <hi>Why haſt thou troubled us? the Lord ſhall trouble thee this day;</hi> and that paſſage to a <hi>ſtory</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the <hi>Chapter,</hi> take it briefly; when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> beſieged <hi>Jericho,</hi> God charged them to <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain</hi> from the <hi>plunder</hi> of the <hi>City. Achar</hi> tranſgreſſed the <hi>command,</hi> and the <hi>people</hi> (hitherto <hi>victorious</hi>) aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulting
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37590:9"/>
                     <hi>Ai,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">v. 5.</note> were <hi>repelled</hi> by the <hi>inhabitants</hi> of that place, ſo that <hi>their hearts melted, and became as water. Joſhua</hi> their <hi>Leader,</hi> ſenſible of this <hi>diſaſter, pleads</hi> with God in an humble <hi>prayer.</hi> But the <hi>Majeſty of Heaven</hi> was <hi>provoked; Divine Juſtice</hi> muſt be <hi>ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi> If <hi>Iſrael ſin,</hi> why ſhould not <hi>Iſrael ſmart? The Lord ſaid unto</hi> Joſhua, <hi>Get thee up,
<note place="margin">v. 10.11.12.</note> wherefore lieſt thou thus upon thy face? Iſrael hath ſinned, therefore they could not ſtand before their enemies.</hi> To <hi>evince</hi> the truth, all the <hi>Tribes</hi> muſt be <hi>aſsembled,</hi> that the <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor</hi> might be <hi>detected.</hi> What is the <hi>iſſue?</hi> A <hi>fatallot</hi> diſcovers <hi>Achan</hi> to be the <hi>man. Joſhua arraigns</hi> him, he <hi>pleads guilty;</hi> the <hi>prize</hi> in his poſſeſſion <hi>witneſſeth</hi> againſt <hi>him,</hi> beſides his own <hi>acknowledgement.</hi> The <hi>committing</hi> that <hi>ſin</hi> cauſed the <hi>peoples defeat;</hi> and thus was Achar <hi>the troubler of Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What <hi>miſery</hi> may <hi>One</hi> mans <hi>ſin</hi> bring upon a whole <hi>multitude?</hi> The Hebrewes call <hi>ungodly men</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Thoſe that be <hi>irreligious</hi> towards <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>debauched</hi> in their <hi>manners,</hi> are <hi>troubleſome</hi> to the <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi> If the World be a <hi>Sea,</hi> theſe raiſe the <hi>ſtorms,</hi> which make our <hi>Voyage turbulent</hi> and <hi>unquiet.</hi> They <hi>want peace</hi> in <hi>themſelves,</hi> and <hi>diſturb</hi> the <hi>peace</hi> of their <hi>Neighbours; wreſting</hi> Gods <hi>judgements</hi> out of his <hi>hands,</hi> and <hi>forcing</hi> his <hi>wrath</hi> upon the <hi>place</hi> of their abode. Theſe <hi>Bees</hi> have their <hi>ſtrings.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 118.12. Iſal. 57.20.5.</note> Theſe <hi>troubled waters</hi> caſt up their <hi>dirt.</hi> Theſe <hi>thorns prick the fingers</hi> of ſuch as are <hi>about</hi> them. <hi>Phineas</hi> (as <hi>Ambaſſadour</hi>) expoſtulating with <hi>Reuben</hi> and <hi>Gad</hi> for their <hi>new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>framed Altar, fears</hi> their <hi>ſuppoſed</hi> ſin would prove <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious</hi> to the whole <hi>multitude; it ſhall be, ſeeing ye Rebel to day againſt the Lord, that to morrow he will be wroth with the whole congregation of Iſrael,</hi> Joſh. 22.18. Here was a <hi>caſe</hi> beyond <hi>fear,</hi> put out of <hi>doubt</hi>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:37590:10"/>by the <hi>ſad event.
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.18.</note> One ſinner deſtroyeth much good: oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioneth</hi> much <hi>miſchief.</hi> The whole <hi>army</hi> ſuffers by a <hi>particular perſon,</hi> Achar <hi>the troubler of Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What ſhall we ſay then?
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.5, 6.</note> Is God unrighteous, that taketh vengeance? God forbid:</hi> But if <hi>one</hi> man <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>wrath</hi> come upon <hi>more,</hi> can this be <hi>reconciled</hi> with <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> and <hi>juſtice?
<note place="margin">1 King. 21.29.</note> yes,</hi> well enough. Ahabs <hi>ſon</hi> may ſmart for Ahabs <hi>fault, the iniquity of the fathers may be viſited upon the children.</hi> Chams <hi>curſe</hi> may be <hi>entailed</hi> upon his <hi>poſterity:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod 20.5.</note> nay, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> may be <hi>beaten</hi> for <hi>Achars transgreſſion.</hi> Obſerve therefore that the Almighty proceeds <hi>otherwiſe</hi> in <hi>temporal</hi> than <hi>eternal puniſhments.</hi> The <hi>laſt</hi> come <hi>wholly</hi> and <hi>ſingly</hi> for our <hi>own impieties:
<note place="margin">Ezek. 18.4.</note> The ſoul that ſinneth it ſhall die.</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> may <hi>overtake</hi> us for the <hi>impieties</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> but ſtill with reſpect to our <hi>particular guilt.</hi> Thereby we are <hi>liable</hi> to the <hi>ſtrokes</hi> of <hi>Divine vengeance;</hi> onely an <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity</hi> is taken to <hi>puniſh</hi> when ſome <hi>notorious of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence</hi> is <hi>committed</hi> by <hi>another,</hi> our <hi>own wickedneſs</hi> is the <hi>impulſive cauſe deſerving,</hi> theirs <hi>the occaſion bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> down theſe <hi>judgements.</hi> A <hi>company of boyes</hi> by ſome <hi>untowardneſs</hi> diſpleaſe their <hi>Maſter,</hi> but at <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> no <hi>noiſe</hi> is made of it: Their <hi>fellow-ſcholler</hi> runs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>fouler crime,</hi> and the <hi>Maſter</hi> layes <hi>hold</hi> of that <hi>ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to <hi>correct</hi> them <hi>all.</hi> Had not this <hi>one</hi> boy done <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs;</hi> all might poſſibly have <hi>eſcaped</hi> that <hi>whipping:</hi> yet is not the <hi>Maſter unjuſt,</hi> in taking ſo <hi>fair an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion</hi> of giving them their <hi>deſerts. Sic parvis compone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re magna ſolemus.</hi> The application of this <hi>ſimile</hi> is <hi>clear,</hi> I would it might <hi>affeci</hi> our <hi>hearts</hi> as well as <hi>convince</hi> our <hi>underſtandings.</hi> God hath <hi>viſited</hi> our <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> with <hi>beavy judgements;</hi> An <hi>unnatural war</hi> broke out in its <hi>bowels,</hi> and the <hi>ſword</hi> was made <hi>drunk</hi> with the <hi>blood</hi> of our <hi>Brethren:</hi> Mens <hi>rights</hi> were invaded
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37590:10"/>by the <hi>Keepers of their liberties.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> was ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by pretended <hi>Patrons</hi> of the <hi>ſtate:</hi> and the <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the faith</hi> murdered under <hi>diſguiſe</hi> of <hi>ſecuring Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> The <hi>force of Law</hi> was interrupted by the <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of power,</hi> and ſome men would own no <hi>authority</hi> but what <hi>hung by their ſide.</hi> Whence came theſe <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles?</hi> from <hi>ſin,</hi> without queſtion. And though the <hi>beſt</hi> cannot excuſe himſelf from <hi>contributing</hi> too <hi>much</hi> to the <hi>common calamities,</hi> (each one <hi>heaping fuel</hi> upon the <hi>fire</hi>) yet might we not plainly ſee there was a <hi>viperous brood</hi> among us, lay <hi>gnawing</hi> at their <hi>Mothers heart;</hi> Men who by <hi>heynous wickedneſs,</hi> became ſo many <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chars, troublers of our Iſrael?</hi> In <hi>mercy</hi> to the land, a <hi>period</hi> was put to the <hi>diſmall days.</hi> Heaven <hi>ſmiled</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us afreſh: and the <hi>joy</hi> of our <hi>hearts</hi> was legible in the <hi>cheerfulneſs</hi> of our <hi>looks:</hi> when <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> obtained a <hi>reſettlement</hi> by the <hi>reſtauration</hi> of our <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign.</hi> But have not theſe <hi>Achars</hi> been at <hi>work</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? <hi>Cauſes</hi> are beſt known by their <hi>effects,</hi> and thoſe effects, have been <hi>felt</hi> to purpoſe. The <hi>ſheathed Sword</hi> was drawn through the <hi>rage</hi> of our <hi>inſulting adverſaries.</hi> Nay the <hi>Almighties Sword</hi> ſlew our <hi>people</hi> by <hi>thouſands.</hi> Our <hi>Royal City</hi> became a <hi>burnt-offering:</hi> and as the <hi>dreadfull peſtilence</hi> ſwept away <hi>men</hi> from their <hi>dwellings:</hi> ſo the <hi>devouring fire</hi> ſwept away their <hi>dwellings</hi> from the <hi>ſurviving men.</hi> The <hi>inhabitants</hi> were reduced into <hi>duſt,</hi> and their <hi>houſes</hi> turned into <hi>aſhes.</hi> Yet all this while <hi>God</hi> was <hi>juſt.</hi> But is it not time then to <hi>find</hi> out theſe <hi>diſturbers</hi> of our <hi>peace,</hi> theſe <hi>occaſioners</hi> of our <hi>troubles,</hi> theſe <hi>provokers</hi> of his <hi>wrath?</hi> They will ſoon be <hi>diſcovered</hi> upon a <hi>diligent enquiry.</hi> For therefore are they <hi>troublers</hi> becauſe <hi>tranſgreſſors, Achar the troubler of Iſrael, who tranſgreſſed in the thing accurſed.</hi> And thus I am come to the <hi>particular</hi> part
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37590:11"/>of the <hi>indictment, who tranſgreſſed in the thing accurſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 A <hi>command</hi> (as you heard there was that no hand ſhould be <hi>laid</hi> upon the <hi>ſpoile</hi> of <hi>Jericho: ye in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiſe keep your ſelves from the accurſed thing, leſt ye make your ſelves accurſed, when you take of the accurſed thing, and make the camp of Iſrael a curſe, and trouble it,</hi> Joſh. 6, 18. It was the Almighties <hi>charge;</hi> who not only <hi>prohibited</hi> the people from <hi>medling,</hi> but <hi>reſerved</hi> it for his own <hi>treaſury. All the ſilver, and the gold and veſſels of braſs and Iron, are conſecrated unto the Lord, they ſhall come into the treaſury of the Lord</hi> v. 19. <hi>Achan</hi> through a <hi>greedy humour,</hi> diſobeys, He <hi>ſaw,</hi> he <hi>coveted,</hi> he <hi>took</hi> a <hi>Babyloniſh garment,</hi> 200 <hi>ſhekels of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and a wedge of gold.</hi> Theſe he <hi>hid,</hi> to paſs <hi>undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered;</hi> and undiſcovered he <hi>was,</hi> till the <hi>lot</hi> fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>him:</hi> that lot extorts a <hi>confeſſion</hi> from his <hi>mouth;</hi> the <hi>prize</hi> is found by the <hi>ſearchers</hi> of his <hi>tent</hi> and laid before the <hi>multitude.</hi> Whence we gather that this perſon was <hi>guilty</hi> of a <hi>double crime: Theft, and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Theft, in taking what was not his own: Sacriledge, in taking what belonged unto God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theft, in taking what was not his own.</hi> It is one <hi>precept</hi> in the <hi>moral Law,
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.15.</note> Thou ſhalt not ſteal:</hi> the <hi>ground</hi> whereof is a <hi>propriety</hi> given to <hi>every man</hi> in his <hi>own goods,</hi> to <hi>Keep</hi> and <hi>uſe</hi> them at his own <hi>pleaſure.</hi> Nay, the ſame God who hath <hi>tied</hi> up our <hi>hands</hi> from <hi>ſteal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">17.</note> hath <hi>reſtrained</hi> our <hi>hearts</hi> from <hi>deſiring: Thou ſhalt not covet thy neighbours houſe, nor any thing that is his.</hi> He allows <hi>no graſping</hi> the <hi>poſſeſſions</hi> of our <hi>brethren,</hi> nor <hi>carving</hi> our ſelves a <hi>ſhare</hi> of their <hi>wealth.</hi> We have nothing to do to <hi>leap</hi> into their <hi>houses,</hi> or <hi>ſeize</hi> upon their <hi>eſtates;</hi> yea <hi>we ſin</hi> if our very <hi>riches</hi> be <hi>irregular,</hi> which ſin will bring <hi>a diſquietment</hi> upon our ſelves; for if <hi>Ahab</hi> by force took <hi>Naboths vineyard,</hi> the <hi>threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:37590:11"/>of God ſhall make him <hi>tremble:</hi> and <hi>occaſion a trouble</hi> to the <hi>place</hi> where we live; for if <hi>Achar</hi> ſteal he is <hi>the troubler of Iſrael, by tranſgreſſing in the thing accurſed.</hi> Time was during the <hi>Goſpels infancy,</hi> when all things were had without <hi>diſtinction. Neither ſaid any man that ought of the things which he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed was his own; but they had all things common,</hi> Acts 4.32. But as St. <hi>Hierome</hi> well; <hi>Diſtingue tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora &amp; concordabunt ſcripturae; obſerve the difference of times, and no difference will be found in the ſcriptures.</hi> The <hi>perſecuted believers</hi> were drawn to ſuch <hi>exigence</hi> that for <hi>ſupport</hi> of thoſe <hi>profeſſing</hi> the ſame <hi>faith;</hi> there was need of <hi>ſharing</hi> in the ſame <hi>poſſeſſions.</hi> Beſides, the <hi>diſtribution</hi> they made was <hi>voluntary,</hi> not <hi>conſtrained:</hi> no <hi>force</hi> of Law <hi>compelled,</hi> but only <hi>freeneſs</hi> of heart <hi>enclined</hi> them. I add the <hi>owners</hi> of <hi>eſtates</hi> had then ſuch a <hi>right,</hi> as admitted no <hi>diſpute,</hi> till <hi>parted</hi> with by their own <hi>conſent. They</hi> had (if the diſtinction may be <hi>pertinent</hi>) <hi>jus ad rem,</hi> they afforded their <hi>brethren jus in re. Whiles it remained, was it not thine own, and after it was ſold, was it not in thine own power?</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Ananias</hi> about the <hi>ſale</hi> of his <hi>land,</hi> Acts 5.4. But when thoſe <hi>neceſſities</hi> were no longer <hi>pleadable;</hi> when the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and its <hi>favourers</hi> began to <hi>flouriſh,</hi> this <hi>temporary community</hi> was <hi>turned</hi> out of <hi>doores;</hi> mens <hi>rights</hi> and <hi>properties</hi> were not only <hi>preferred,</hi> but <hi>ſtricter encloſures</hi> made about them, by <hi>ſevere edicts</hi> of <hi>pious Princes,</hi> againſt all <hi>violence</hi> and <hi>theft,</hi> under <hi>grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous</hi> and <hi>heavy penalties:</hi> and <hi>ſtealing</hi> as a <hi>palpable breach</hi> both of <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Humane lawes,</hi> made the <hi>offender</hi> liable, not only to the <hi>wrath</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> but to the <hi>ſentence</hi> of the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate:</hi> as before the Goſpels <hi>publiſhings,</hi> ſuch men <hi>eſcaped</hi> not a <hi>condigne puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> We ſee it in the <hi>example</hi> before us; <hi>Achar</hi> was
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37590:12"/>
                     <hi>ſtoned,</hi> his <hi>ſtollen goods</hi> were <hi>burnt; becauſe he tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed in the thing accurſed,</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> Branch of his <hi>Crime.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Sacriledge.</hi> As he <hi>ſtole,</hi> ſo he ſtole from <hi>God,</hi> who had paſſed a <hi>conſecration</hi> upon the <hi>goods</hi> of <hi>Jericho,</hi> and <hi>deſigned</hi> them for his own <hi>Exchequer.</hi> It is ill making <hi>too bold</hi> with the <hi>Almighty.</hi> If the <hi>Eagle</hi> ſnatch a <hi>coal</hi> from the <hi>Altar,</hi> in all likelihood ſhe <hi>burns</hi> her <hi>neſt;</hi> and if <hi>Achar</hi> be too <hi>buſy</hi> with the <hi>hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed ſpoil,</hi> it may bring a <hi>miſchief</hi> upon his own <hi>head.</hi> Therefore (I preſume) called <hi>the thing accurſed, ab effectu,</hi> by laying him open to the <hi>curſe of God,</hi> and to the <hi>vengeance of men.</hi> Nor can they who commit <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chars fault</hi> expect any better than Achars <hi>reward. Will a man rob God? yet ye have robbed me: but ye ſay, wherein have we robbed thee? In Tithes and Offerings. Ye are curſed with a curſe: for ye have robbed me, even this whole Nation,</hi> Mal. 3.8.9. And not without good <hi>ground.</hi> Things are commonly devoted to God <hi>cum Anathemate,</hi> with an <hi>Anathema</hi> againſt ſuch as ſhall <hi>convert</hi> them to <hi>private uſes;</hi> (We ſee it in the <hi>precedents</hi> of <hi>ancient Dedications</hi>) whereby he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſtrongly <hi>inveſted</hi> in the <hi>right</hi> to and <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of them: ſo that a <hi>ſacrilegious perſon</hi> is not only a <hi>Thief</hi> in the <hi>higheſt degree,</hi> but <hi>a direct contemner of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Majeſty;</hi> who is neither ſo <hi>weak</hi> that he <hi>cannot,</hi> nor ſo <hi>tame</hi> that he <hi>will not</hi> puniſh the <hi>violations</hi> of his own <hi>intereſt.</hi> Thoſe that would not <hi>believe</hi> have to their <hi>coſt, experienced</hi> the <hi>truth</hi> hereof; and they who by ſuch <hi>examples,</hi> will not be <hi>perſwaded,</hi> ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after <hi>pay</hi> at a <hi>dear rate</hi> for their <hi>incredulity.</hi> If they loſe not their <hi>ſouls,</hi> (for <hi>repentance</hi> and <hi>reſtitution</hi> may ſecure them) yet many times they loſe their <hi>eſtates: one generation</hi> often ſees the <hi>beginning</hi> and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37590:12"/>
                     <hi>end</hi> of their wealth. <hi>Sacrilegious gain</hi> proves a <hi>Canker</hi> in the <hi>faireſt Inheritance,</hi> and <hi>eates</hi> out the <hi>profit</hi> of our <hi>juſteſt incomes.</hi> Nay, many times it coſts men their <hi>lives. King Rufus</hi> his <hi>ſtory</hi> need not be mentioned: there is an <hi>authentick inſtance</hi> in the Text, of one <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, convicted, condemned,</hi> and <hi>executed;</hi> Achar, <hi>the troubler of Iſrael, who tranſgreſſed in the thing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You have ſeen <hi>the priſoner arraigned,</hi> his <hi>Indictment drawn up</hi> with an account of <hi>the Crimes</hi> laid againſt him. But this <hi>Honourable Aſſembly</hi> challengeth ſome further <hi>tribute</hi> of duty, which ſhall be confined to the <hi>ſands</hi> in the <hi>glaſs,</hi> for fear of <hi>interrupting</hi> the <hi>concerns</hi> of the <hi>Countrey.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And I hope the preſumption will be <hi>pardoned,</hi> if my <hi>firſt addreſs</hi> be made to <hi>your Lordſhips,</hi> whom <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Vice-gerent</hi> have employed in this <hi>Circuit,</hi> to ſearch out theſe Achars, <hi>who trouble our Iſrael.</hi> No hopes <hi>England</hi> ſhould be a <hi>Land of Peace</hi> till it be a <hi>Land of righteouſneſs.</hi> No thoughts it ſhould be free from <hi>vexatious troubles,</hi> ſo long as it is full of <hi>notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſinners.</hi> We humbly beſeech <hi>your Lordſhips</hi> to <hi>knit</hi> your <hi>browes,</hi> to <hi>ſharpen</hi> your <hi>tongues, ſeverely</hi> to <hi>frown, ſtrictly</hi> to <hi>chide, und auntedly</hi> to <hi>puniſh</hi> ſuch <hi>wicked</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: yea though <hi>Achar-like, deſcended from the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtock of</hi> Judah: well conſidering, that if <hi>Great men be not Suns to enlighten, they will prove Comets to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect their inferiours.</hi> Let not <hi>prophanneſs</hi> eſcape, though in <hi>a gentle habit,</hi> nor the <hi>ruſtling of an offenders Silks</hi> plead for an <hi>exemption</hi> from your <hi>juſt cenſure. He,</hi> whom you <hi>repreſent,</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>no accepter of perſons.</hi> And ſo ſhall you ſhew yourſelves <hi>Gods</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, when thus taking <hi>pattern</hi> from <hi>God</hi> himſelf.</p>
                  <p>Nor do we queſtion, but thoſe <hi>Honourable, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37590:13"/>Worthy Perſons, Aſſiſtants on the Bench,</hi> will <hi>contribute</hi> their help to ſo <hi>pious</hi> a <hi>work.</hi> Beſides thoſe <hi>arguments</hi> which might be drawn from ſeveral <hi>Topicks,</hi> (and all of them ſufficiently <hi>perſwaſive</hi>) <hi>Gods Glory, Religions Credit, your own Eternal Reputation,</hi> let <hi>the honour and ſafety of your Countrey</hi> prevail upon your <hi>generous ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> which elſe muſt be ſadly <hi>hazarded;</hi> (I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſaid <hi>utterly loſt</hi>) for every <hi>Achar</hi> will be a <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler of Iſrael,</hi> if allowed to <hi>tranſgreſs in the thing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But before ſuch men can fall under the <hi>Courts ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> I preſume they muſt paſs the <hi>teſt</hi> of, or at leaſt be <hi>preſented</hi> by the <hi>Grand Jury.</hi> And of thoſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the <hi>Name of God,</hi> I intreat this <hi>favour,</hi> that as <hi>the Countreys-eye,</hi> they will diſcover theſe <hi>offenders,</hi> who are like to prove <hi>the Countries trouble.</hi> 'Tis fit an employment of ſo <hi>ſo high importance,</hi> ſhould be managed by <hi>perſons of great worth:</hi> men of ſuch <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacity,</hi> that <hi>Achar may not lurk in his Tent;</hi> and of ſuch <hi>integrity,</hi> that neither his <hi>ſilver ſhekels,</hi> nor his <hi>wedge of gold</hi> may render him <hi>ſecure.</hi> This <hi>County</hi> is happy in the <hi>Gentries</hi> undertaking the <hi>toyle</hi> of this <hi>work,</hi> which indeed they are <hi>beſt</hi> to be concerned in. They need not <hi>fear</hi> the <hi>diſpleaſure</hi> of a <hi>vicious Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord,</hi> or a <hi>malicious Neighbour,</hi> which <hi>ſtrikes terror</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hearts of <hi>ordinary perſons.</hi> They are out of the <hi>reach</hi> of theſe <hi>promiſes</hi> and <hi>threats,</hi> which will either <hi>allure</hi> or <hi>terrifie</hi> inferiours. And ſuch (I hope) will be employed in the <hi>buſineſs</hi> of this <hi>Aſſizes; impartial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenters</hi> of <hi>(Achars) faults; theft</hi> and <hi>ſacriledge. Theft;</hi> that men may <hi>enjoy</hi> what <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Laws</hi> have made their <hi>own:</hi> that their <hi>eſtates</hi> be not <hi>ſeized,</hi> nor their <hi>juſt intereſts</hi> expoſed to the <hi>rapacious hands</hi> of <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Robbers.</hi> And truly (Gentlemen) there
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37590:13"/>is another <hi>theft</hi> might be worth your conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Theologi detractio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem furto pejorem ſtatuunt; uter<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> reſtitutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, latro ſcil. et de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractor; ſed multo facilius ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis fit pro furto quam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractione; quia in illo quantitas damni cognoſci et eſtimari poteſt, in il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. Epiſc. Davenant in Coloſs. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 7 <hi>Machia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel. Aquin.</hi> 2.2. <hi>qu.</hi> 99. <hi>Art.</hi> 3. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> conc.</hi>
                     </note> the <hi>ſtealing from a man his good Name and Credit: Reputation</hi> is one of the <hi>greateſt bleſſings</hi> upon earth, which if once <hi>aſſaulted,</hi> the <hi>Scars</hi> thereof are <hi>carried</hi> to our <hi>Graves.</hi> That <hi>Helliſh Politician</hi> was too <hi>cunning</hi> in his <hi>Maxime, Calu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mniare audacter, aliquid adherebit: Strike home</hi> in your <hi>ſlander,</hi> and if the <hi>blow</hi> do not <hi>kill,</hi> be ſure it will <hi>wound.</hi> It is certain our <hi>laws</hi> have <hi>provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> againſt this <hi>evill,</hi> it is your <hi>care</hi> the <hi>offenders</hi> be <hi>known.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But when <hi>God</hi> is engaged as well as <hi>man,</hi> your diligence muſt be <hi>ſingular</hi> to <hi>vindicate</hi> him True, he is a <hi>patient</hi> in every <hi>Crime,</hi> (as all ſins <hi>ſtrike</hi> againſt his <hi>law</hi>) but more <hi>eſpecially</hi> in <hi>ſome</hi> than in others; and in none more than this of <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> A <hi>word</hi> of as <hi>large</hi> a <hi>comprehenſion,</hi> as the <hi>thing</hi> is of a <hi>peſtilent nature.</hi> It is uſually recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of three ſorts; with relation to <hi>things, to places,</hi> and <hi>to perſons.</hi> The <hi>laſt Ages</hi> have had <hi>Wide throats,</hi> and greedily <hi>ſwallowed</hi> many <hi>holy Morſels.</hi> What is <hi>paſt</hi> lies not within your power to <hi>remedy;</hi> but if any <hi>ravenous Harpie</hi> be <hi>faſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> upon that which <hi>remains,</hi> be ſo <hi>juſt</hi> to God to <hi>beat him off,</hi> and <hi>pluck</hi> it out of his <hi>Claws. Secure his Portion,</hi> and reſt <hi>ſatisfied</hi> he will <hi>ſecure</hi> your <hi>eſtates.</hi> Caſt an eye upon the <hi>Holy places,</hi> and let them <hi>partake</hi> a little of your <hi>care,</hi> ſuffer not our <hi>Churches</hi> to be <hi>excommunicated,</hi> nor our <hi>Congregations</hi> to be gathered into <hi>Barns,</hi> whilſt the <hi>Houſes of God</hi> ſtand too too <hi>empty:</hi> Certainly there is <hi>a relative holineſs</hi> in them, by their <hi>ſolemn dedication</hi> to <hi>Gods ſervice:</hi> if ſo, this offence is <hi>Sacriledge;</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Aquinas</hi> was <hi>miſtaken,</hi> by whom it is <hi>defined,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37590:14"/>Sacrae rei violati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aquin.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>Q.</hi> 99 <hi>Art.</hi> 1. <hi>reſp. ad arg.</hi> 3. <hi>Gravius peccatum est ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium quò peccatur contra per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonam ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram, quam quò peccatur contra lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum ſacrum Aquin.</hi> 2. 2 <hi>qu.</hi> 99. <hi>Art</hi> 3. Exod. 15.11.</note> and that <hi>violatio</hi> interpreted by <hi>quaecuncue irreverentia.</hi> But the <hi>Schools</hi> agree, the <hi>hainouſeſt Sacriledge</hi> is againſt a <hi>Perſon,</hi> and what perſon <hi>greater</hi> than God? All <hi>holy things</hi> chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge a <hi>reverence</hi> by Vertue of their <hi>holineſs, He</hi> moſt of <hi>all</hi> who hath ſtiled himſelf <hi>glorious in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</hi> Do not thou <hi>overlook</hi> any thing which may <hi>reflect</hi> upon <hi>Him.</hi> If you find that <hi>his Name be blaſphemed,</hi> that <hi>his word</hi> be <hi>profaned,</hi> that <hi>his Ordinances be contemned,</hi> that <hi>his day be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hallowed</hi> (and alas! theſe <hi>ſins</hi> are too <hi>common</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us) for <hi>Gods ſake</hi> let them not <hi>eſcape</hi> an <hi>eſpeciall remark</hi> from <hi>you,</hi> nor the <hi>offenders</hi> ſome <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious rebukes</hi> from <hi>your Lordſhips.</hi> Pardon my <hi>zeal</hi> in theſe <hi>paſſionate wiſhes; Gods honour</hi> muſt be <hi>regarded</hi> if ever we expect to be <hi>happy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I fear being tedious, and therefore will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. May all who are concerned in the <hi>affairs</hi> of theſe <hi>days,</hi> either as <hi>Jurors,</hi> or <hi>Witneſses,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of <hi>Achars faults.</hi> If once <hi>forſworn,</hi> you are <hi>guilty of them both.</hi> In caſe you are employed <hi>between party and party,</hi> you <hi>rob</hi> your <hi>neighbour</hi> of his <hi>goods,</hi> either by <hi>procuring</hi> or <hi>confirming an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt title.</hi> If between <hi>the King</hi> and <hi>the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> you either <hi>rob your Soveraign of a ſubject by condemning the innocent,</hi> or you ſteal <hi>from juſtice by acquitting the guilty.</hi> Beſides God hath ſtamped <hi>holineſs</hi> upon an <hi>Oath.</hi> Therein men <hi>uſe his name,</hi> they call him <hi>to witneſs the truth of their words;</hi> therefore <hi>Perjury</hi> is a <hi>branch of Sacriledge,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 20.7.</note> and as <hi>ſuch</hi> it ſhall be <hi>rewarded; for the Lord will not hold him guiltleſs, that taketh his Name in vain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Once</hi> more I return to your <hi>Lordſhips;</hi> and preſent <hi>Achar</hi> not as <hi>ſtanding at the Bar,</hi> but as <hi>lying in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37590:14"/>his Priſon. Places</hi> of that <hi>nature</hi> were certainly <hi>deſigned</hi> to be <hi>houſes of inſtructions,</hi> as well as of <hi>correction:</hi> that however the <hi>body</hi> might <hi>ſuffer,</hi> the <hi>ſoul</hi> might be <hi>bettered:</hi> that however the <hi>guilty</hi> might <hi>ſmart for their faults before men,</hi> they might <hi>be drawn to repentance before God.</hi> That if the <hi>Crimes</hi> they committed <hi>deſerved death, helps</hi> might not be wanting to <hi>prepare them for it:</hi> and if through the <hi>laws clemency,</hi> they <hi>came off with life,</hi> their former <hi>reſtraint</hi> might be a <hi>dayly Monitor</hi> to warn them againſt <hi>ſuch ungodly courſes.</hi> But <hi>experience</hi> proves <hi>Goals</hi> are <hi>Goals</hi> in a <hi>double ſenſe; fellons</hi> are held as <hi>faſt</hi> in <hi>the fetters of ſin,</hi> as in the <hi>fetters of Iron:</hi> and it is <hi>hard</hi> for a man to <hi>enter</hi> the <hi>Priſon a child of hell,</hi> but he <hi>leaves</hi> it <hi>ten times worſe.</hi> It might not be <hi>unworthy of your Lordſhips</hi> to think of this <hi>particular</hi> along your <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit.</hi> Here (God be bleſſed) through the <hi>charity</hi> of <hi>Benefactors</hi> a <hi>proviſion</hi> is made for <hi>teaching</hi> the <hi>priſoners:</hi> in ſome <hi>other places</hi> I am ſure it is <hi>not,</hi> where at this <hi>time</hi> it <hi>needs</hi> ſufficiently.
<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therfore to conſider the <hi>condition</hi> of thoſe <hi>poor creatures;</hi> that your <hi>ſentence</hi> from the <hi>bench ſpeak not death</hi> both to <hi>body and ſoul.</hi> It will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be an <hi>act</hi> of the <hi>higheſt compaſſion,</hi> and an <hi>imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> the <hi>example</hi> of that good <hi>Joſhua,</hi> who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to <hi>work</hi> ſo <hi>effectually</hi> with <hi>Achar,</hi> that the ſame <hi>ſtones</hi> might <hi>not kill him</hi> and <hi>damn him.</hi> Let them <hi>ſuffer</hi> under your <hi>juſtice</hi> here, ſo they <hi>meet not</hi> with <hi>Divine vengeance</hi> hereafter. The ſum of all is, <hi>God muſt not be diſhonoured, Iſrael muſt not be troubled, Laws muſt not be infringed, Achars muſt not be ſpared.</hi> And then will our <hi>land</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>tranquility;</hi> the <hi>bleſſing of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37590:15"/>will <hi>reſt</hi> upon our <hi>heads;</hi> we ſhall <hi>partake</hi> of his <hi>preſent favour,</hi> and in due time of his <hi>future Glory.</hi> Which <hi>God</hi> grant we way <hi>all</hi> do, through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> To whom with the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> be <hi>Honour, Praiſe,</hi> and <hi>Dominion,</hi> henceforth, and for evermore. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:37590:15"/>
                  <p>THE Righteous Man's Concern, FOR THE Churches Miſery. A SERMON Preached before the Judges at St. <hi>Maries</hi> Church in <hi>Leice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, July,</hi> 22. 1669.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Tho. Stanhope A.M.</hi> Vicar of St. <hi>Margarets</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:37590:16"/>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:37590:16"/>
                  <head>The Righteous Mans Concern for the Churches Miſery.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſalm 11.3.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>If the foundations be deſtroyed, what can the Righteous do?</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Oly Men have uſually <hi>met</hi> with their <hi>ſhare</hi> of <hi>troubles.</hi> The way to <hi>heaven</hi> is <hi>paved</hi> with <hi>flints,</hi> and <hi>ſtrawed</hi> with <hi>Roſes.</hi> Our world is a <hi>Sea,</hi> and the <hi>beſt ſail</hi> through it, with <hi>the wind in their faces.</hi> That <hi>Royall Prophet</hi> to whoſe <hi>compoſure</hi> this pſalm <hi>pretends,</hi> though by the <hi>infallible ſpirit,</hi> declared <hi>a man after Gods heart,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts. 13.22. 18 am. 26.20.</note> was ſufficiently <hi>ſenſible</hi> how <hi>dear</hi> a <hi>rate</hi> his piety <hi>coſt</hi> him with a <hi>wicked Saul,</hi> who <hi>ſought</hi> his <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>endeavoured</hi> his <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Hunted</hi> he was <hi>like a Patridge,</hi> and then no marvell his <hi>enemies</hi> ſhould ſay, <hi>flee as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:37590:17"/>to your Mountain</hi> V. 1. <hi>Saul</hi> and his <hi>Paraſites</hi> had <hi>knit</hi> their <hi>brows,</hi> and then no wonder if <hi>they bent their bows;</hi> they <hi>ſhot</hi> forth their <hi>bitter words,</hi> a ſign <hi>they made ready their Arrows upon the ſtring:</hi> and all this preparation was to <hi>wound</hi> that <hi>good man,</hi> and <hi>thoſe</hi> who were <hi>like</hi> him: <hi>privily to ſhoot at the upright in heart.</hi> V. 2. Yet as <hi>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſouls</hi> preferr the <hi>publick concernes</hi> before their <hi>private intereſts,</hi> he <hi>values</hi> not what related to <hi>himſelf,</hi> in reſpect of what referred to the <hi>Church of God.</hi> If <hi>ſhe</hi> fared <hi>ill he</hi> could not fare <hi>well.</hi> And appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending her <hi>foundations</hi> in <hi>danger</hi> of being <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned,</hi> he breaks forth into the <hi>queſtion</hi> before us: <hi>if the foundations be deſtroyed, what can the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous do?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In which words you may pleaſe to obſerve two general parts 1. <hi>A Suppoſition.</hi> 2. <hi>An In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogation. A Suppoſition, if the foundations be deſtroyed. An interrogation; What can the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous do?</hi> In the <hi>Suppoſition</hi> there is the <hi>matter,</hi> and the <hi>form:</hi> or the <hi>Suppoſitum,</hi> and the <hi>modus ſupponendi.</hi> In the <hi>Suppoſitum,</hi> the <hi>ſubject,</hi> and the <hi>predicate:</hi> the <hi>ſubject the foundations;</hi> the <hi>predicate deſtroyed.</hi> In the <hi>modus ſupponendi;</hi> take notice of three things, for the word <hi>if</hi> will bear them al; 1. the <hi>poſſibility of it,</hi> the <hi>foundations may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayed.</hi> 2. <hi>the iniquity of it.</hi> It is <hi>a very wicked thing to deſtroy them.</hi> 3. the <hi>miſeny or calamity which attends it:</hi> it will be a <hi>ſad</hi> thing <hi>if the foundations be deſtroyed.</hi> The <hi>Second</hi> general is <hi>the Interrogation; What can the Righteous do?</hi> or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſome <hi>tranſlations, What hath the Righteous done?</hi> both may be taken in under three notions; 1. as <hi>vox reflectentis.</hi> 2. as <hi>vox de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorantis.</hi>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:37590:17"/>3. as <hi>vox inquirentis.</hi> The <hi>firſtagrees</hi> eſpecially with the <hi>old:</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> with <hi>both:</hi> and the <hi>third</hi> with the <hi>new reading;</hi> of theſe parts in their order. I begin with the <hi>firſt, the Suppoſition;</hi> and therein with</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>The Subject or matter of the ſuppoſitum, the foundations.</hi> I may ſpare the pains to tell you that the <hi>word</hi> is by ſome rendred <hi>ſnares</hi> or <hi>nets:</hi> as if <hi>David</hi> had particularly intended <hi>Sauls deſigns againſt him.</hi> We have nothing to do with it in that <hi>notion,</hi> ſuiting perhaps as little with the <hi>ſence</hi> as with this <hi>occaſion.</hi> Thus far I ſhall <hi>uſe</hi> it and no <hi>further.</hi> May <hi>deſtroying the foundations</hi> prove as great a <hi>ſnare</hi> to all who <hi>endeavour</hi> it, as could <hi>correſpond with Sauls batred,</hi> without <hi>prejudice to Davids innocency.</hi> Omitting therefore the variety of tranſlations, we fix upon the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> where the Metaphor is drawn from a <hi>building,</hi> to which the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> are here <hi>compared:</hi> And not here only but in <hi>other places</hi> too. St. Paul calls <hi>the Church, the houſe of God</hi> 1 Tim. 3.15. <hi>Jeruſalem is builded as a City that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact together,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, Pſ. 12.3. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, where <hi>God</hi> had his <hi>Temple,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> had his <hi>Throne.</hi> And thus we ſhall ſee theſe <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations</hi> are either <hi>foundations of Doctrine, or founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Government,</hi> Take away the <hi>one,</hi> and <hi>the building</hi> will <hi>totter,</hi> for want of its <hi>Jachin,</hi> which doth eſtabliſh it: Take away the <hi>other</hi> and it will <hi>reel</hi> for want of its <hi>Booz,</hi> for <hi>in it is ſtrength.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. There are <hi>foundations of Doctrine.</hi> Thoſe <hi>points</hi> which <hi>comprize</hi> the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;</hi> We ordinarily call them fundamentals. And the <hi>Scripture</hi> uſeth the term in the text,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37590:18"/>Heb. 6.1. <hi>not laying again the foundation of repentance from dead works, and of faith towards God:</hi> which in the beginning of that verſe is ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>the principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> ſuch are <hi>the being and attributes of God, the divinity and humanity of our Saviour, the infallibility and authority of the Scriptures, the immortality of the ſoul, the reſurrection of the body,</hi> and the like: for upon <hi>theſe</hi> we <hi>build</hi> our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;</hi> and the <hi>building</hi> can never <hi>ſtand</hi> unleſs the <hi>foundation</hi> be <hi>firm.</hi> Admit men once to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> theſe <hi>principles</hi> or to be <hi>perſwaded</hi> into a <hi>diſbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief</hi> of them, and never expect to find their <hi>actions ſavour</hi> any thing of <hi>piety</hi> or <hi>honeſty.</hi> It is evidently plain, that a <hi>practical conviction</hi> of theſe <hi>grand truths</hi> hath the greateſt <hi>influence</hi> upon our ſouls, to make us <hi>good ſcrvants</hi> to our <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>good ſubjects</hi> to our <hi>King.</hi> True, the Goſpel <hi>prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily</hi> aims at our <hi>piety,</hi> yet doth it withall <hi>deſign</hi> our <hi>Allegiance:</hi> that with <hi>equall conſcience</hi> we pay the <hi>duties</hi> owing to <hi>the powers on earth,</hi> as we do to <hi>the almighty power of heaven,</hi> I had almoſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got to mention St.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Auguſt.</hi> in loc.</note> 
                     <hi>Auguſtines expoſition</hi> in his. <hi>Hoc di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit contra omnes Hereticos.</hi> For then the Pſalmiſt by <hi>foundations</hi> muſt mean <hi>doctrinall truths,</hi> if <hi>Hereticks</hi> who <hi>pervert theſe truths</hi> be <hi>deſtroyers of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. There are alſo a ſecond ſort of <hi>foundations,</hi> thoſe <hi>of Government;</hi> which we ſuppoſe to be <hi>the fundamental laws</hi> in a <hi>nation grounded</hi> upon the <hi>Maximes</hi> of <hi>naturall</hi> and <hi>Civill Pollicy.</hi> Thus St. <hi>Hierome</hi> expounds the words,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hierom.</hi> in in loc.</note> 
                     <hi>ſi leges diſſipatae ſint, if the laws be diſſolved.</hi> 'Tis well known there is no <hi>civilized,</hi> much leſs <hi>Chriſtian Kingdom,</hi> but hath
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37590:18"/>its <hi>nationall conſtitutions</hi> (if that be not too <hi>low</hi> a word) whereby the <hi>people</hi> are <hi>governed.</hi> God himſelf would not let the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> be <hi>without</hi> them as a means to <hi>uphold ſocieties,</hi> and <hi>keep</hi> every <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> within his due <hi>bounds.</hi> Now as <hi>Lawes</hi> are <hi>virtually lodged</hi> in the <hi>ſupreme Magiſtrate,</hi> ſo as by his <hi>conſent (Le Roy. le veult)</hi> they receive there <hi>ſanction;</hi> ſo in an eſpeciall manner <hi>He</hi> may be <hi>intended</hi> in the text. <hi>David</hi> as a <hi>King,</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>himſelf</hi> at the ſame <hi>rate; the earth, and all the inhabitants thereof are diſſolved, I bear up the Pillars of it.</hi> Pſ. 75.3. And certainly there cannot be a greater <hi>ſhake</hi> given to any <hi>nation</hi> than an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringing the juſt Authority of the Prince,</hi> or of <hi>thoſe</hi> to whom he <hi>commits</hi> either <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> or <hi>Civill Juriſdiction,</hi> I ſay <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> for ſome of the <hi>Rabbins</hi> have been ſo favourable as to name the very <hi>Prieſts</hi> for theſe <hi>foundations.</hi> I dare not plead to ſo much <hi>reading,</hi> but a <hi>worthy Author</hi> aſſerts it to be <hi>Rabbi Solomons</hi> gloſs: <hi>fundamenta</hi> i.e.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vicaris de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capla</hi> in loc.</note> 
                     <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotes, ſuper quos fulciebat ſe populus the Prieſts,</hi> who were the <hi>peoples prop and ſupport.</hi> Wonder not, I ſpeak for our own <hi>order.</hi> It is <hi>pity</hi> we ſhould <hi>loſe</hi> thoſe <hi>priviledges,</hi> which the <hi>bounty</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>his Vice-gerents</hi> have <hi>given</hi> us. Theſe then are the <hi>foundations of doctrine</hi> and <hi>of Government,</hi> the <hi>ſubject</hi> of <hi>the propoſition,</hi> whoſe <hi>predicate</hi> follows.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>The predicate deſtroyed if the foundations be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi> Where the Pſalmiſt ſtill <hi>proſecutes</hi> his <hi>Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor;</hi> for the word ſignifies a <hi>demoliſhing of build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</hi> Not only a <hi>picking ſome ſtones out of the wall,</hi> which yet might be <hi>incomvenient:</hi> nor <hi>beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down</hi> the <hi>higher ſtories</hi> and <hi>upper rooms,</hi> though that would <hi>ſpoil</hi> the <hi>houſes beauty;</hi> but the <hi>laying</hi>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:37590:19"/>it <hi>levell with the ground,</hi> which muſt render it <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly un-inhabitable.</hi> Thus when the <hi>doctrines of Chriſtianity</hi> are <hi>boldly denyed,</hi> and the <hi>laws of a Kingdom inſolently eppoſed,</hi> when <hi>the people ſeditiouſly refuſe</hi> either to be <hi>led</hi> by <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Aaron;</hi> then may we wofully <hi>complain</hi> of <hi>the foundations being deſtroyed.</hi> And ſo I paſs from the firſt thing, <hi>the ſuppoſitum,</hi> to</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>modus ſupponendi,</hi> the <hi>manner of the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſall,</hi> in the word (if) <hi>If the foundations be</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: And here we are firſt preſented with</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>The poſſibility of it.</hi> That theſe <hi>foundations MAY BE deſtroyed:</hi> for <hi>de impoſſibilibus non eſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponendum,</hi> no <hi>wiſe man,</hi> much leſs the <hi>All-wiſe God</hi> would <hi>ſuppoſe impoſſibilities.</hi> And indeed the <hi>truth</hi> hereof doth but too <hi>plainly</hi> appear. No ſooner did the <hi>Son of righteouſneſs begin</hi> to <hi>ſhine,</hi> but <hi>clouds</hi> aroſe to <hi>darken</hi> his <hi>light. Truth</hi> was no ſooner <hi>ſprung out of the earth,</hi> but <hi>errors</hi> began to <hi>peep</hi> out of <hi>hell.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> in her <hi>infancy</hi> was <hi>peſtered</hi> with <hi>Herefies,</hi> and the <hi>tares</hi> grew up as <hi>faſt</hi> as the <hi>wheat.</hi> There was a <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> among <hi>Satans followers,</hi> as there was among <hi>Chriſts diſciples.</hi> A <hi>Simon Magnus</hi> to oppoſe <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Peter:</hi> from whom all the <hi>Hereticks</hi> of later <hi>date derive</hi> their <hi>pedigree. He,</hi> to <hi>raze the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> while the Church was but yet <hi>in building,</hi> contradicts <hi>three main points</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian faith; The Trinity of perſons, Chriſts paſſion,</hi> and <hi>Mans fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture reſurrection.</hi> In <hi>Domitians</hi> time, <hi>Elion</hi> and <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthus</hi> broached their <hi>pernicious opinions</hi> againſt the <hi>Divinity</hi> of our <hi>bleſſed Saviour:</hi> the occaſion (if <hi>good Authors</hi> may be <hi>credited</hi>) why <hi>St. John</hi> (then alive) publiſhed <hi>his Goſpel.</hi> The <hi>Gnoſticks</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:37590:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>had already got <hi>head,</hi> men of ſuch <hi>abominable principles,</hi> and <hi>flagitious practices,</hi> that a <hi>modeſt tongue</hi> and a <hi>chaſt ear</hi> cannot with <hi>Civility,</hi> admit the <hi>naming</hi> them. In <hi>following ages</hi> theſe <hi>Hereticks</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came more <hi>numerous,</hi> and thereby more <hi>miſchievous.</hi> How mightily the <hi>Arrian blaſphemy</hi> prevailed, all <hi>Church-Hiſtories</hi> witneſs: St. <hi>Hieromes</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion though it ſavour of <hi>Rhetorick</hi> may be allowed without any <hi>great Hyperbole; Ingemuit totus mundus, et miratus eſt ſe factum eſſe Arrianum: The world groaned under its burden, and admired to ſee it ſelf devoted to Arrius.</hi> Nay, ſo far were the <hi>Doctors</hi> of the Church <hi>ſeduced,</hi> that <hi>Athunaſius alone ſtickled</hi> conſiderably for the <hi>Orthodox Doctrine:</hi> there was <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus Athanaſius contra totum mundum, et totus contra unum Athanaſium.</hi> It would be tedious to <hi>trace</hi> the <hi>footſteps</hi> of theſe <hi>deſtroyers</hi> to our <hi>days:</hi> Were all <hi>books burnt,</hi> were all <hi>records</hi> of former times <hi>loſt,</hi> could we <hi>betray</hi> our ſelves into ſuch <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulity</hi> that nothing which our <hi>Fathers</hi> have <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered</hi> would <hi>gain</hi> our <hi>belief;</hi> yet if we will <hi>take</hi> up <hi>ſhort</hi> of the <hi>madneſs</hi> to <hi>diſtruſt</hi> our <hi>eyes</hi> and <hi>ears,</hi> we ſhall ſoon perceive a poſſibility of this <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief.</hi> Which of us are ſtrangers to the <hi>Quakers plea</hi> of <hi>perfection,</hi> and <hi>preferring Enthuſtaſticall revelations</hi> above the <hi>Holy Scriptures?</hi> Who knows not that the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> to defend their <hi>not baptizing infants, implead</hi> the doctrine of <hi>Originall ſin?</hi> Some have taken pains to <hi>rob</hi> the <hi>ſoul</hi> of its <hi>happineſs imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after death,</hi> and to <hi>lull</hi> it <hi>aſleep</hi> with the <hi>body</hi> till the <hi>general reſurrection.</hi> Others would <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove</hi> the <hi>ſufficiency</hi> of <hi>Chriſts ſufferings,</hi> and a third ſort would <hi>deveſt</hi> both <hi>Him</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> of their <hi>Godhead.</hi> Theſe things through the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37590:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>licentiouſneſs</hi> of the <hi>Preſs</hi> are expoſed to <hi>publick view</hi> and made too <hi>manifeſt</hi> to be <hi>concealed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Paſs from the <hi>foundations</hi> of <hi>doctrine,</hi> to <hi>thoſe</hi> of <hi>Government.</hi> And have we not ſeen a <hi>poſſibility</hi> of their <hi>deſtruction.</hi> We have lived in <hi>thoſe days</hi> when the <hi>voice of laws</hi> could not be heard for the <hi>claſhing of armour;</hi> when men <hi>defended their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign</hi> by <hi>invading his Authority, and fought for their King with Swords drawn</hi> againſt <hi>him:</hi> when they <hi>put Him in priſon,</hi> to <hi>eſtabliſh Him</hi> in his <hi>throne,</hi> and to make Him <hi>glorious, cut off his head.</hi> And how came theſe things to paſs? Satans <hi>agents</hi> are <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> they do <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in St. <hi>Judes</hi> phraſe <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>furtim intrare, ſteal in</hi> among <hi>well meaning Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>with good words and fair speeches, deceive the hearts of the ſimple.</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> declaring how <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks deſtroy</hi> the <hi>foundations,</hi> ſaith it is done, <hi>In conventiculis ſuis, ubi parvulos et interioris lucis igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros non lacte nutriunt,
<note place="margin">Rom. 16.8. <hi>Aug.</hi> in loc.</note> ſed venenis necant. In their Conventicles, and private meerings,</hi> where theſe <hi>craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty chapmen</hi> inſtead of <hi>nouriſhing</hi> their <hi>ignorant hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> with the <hi>ſincere milk of the word, poiſon</hi> their ſouls with <hi>erroneous doctrines.</hi> Whether or no our <hi>miſeries</hi> have happened by the <hi>ſame means</hi> let <hi>ſober</hi> men <hi>judge;</hi> and if theſe <hi>courſes</hi> be <hi>continued</hi> what the <hi>iſſue</hi> will be, all lovers of <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>truth tremble</hi> to <hi>think.</hi> Certainly <hi>the foundations deſtroyed,</hi> we can neither hope to be <hi>holy</hi> nor <hi>happy;</hi> not <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> for this very <hi>ſuppoſition</hi> doth imply.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>The iniquity of it.</hi> It is a <hi>wicked</hi> thing <hi>if the foundations be deſtroyed.</hi> Can any thing be more <hi>notoriouſly evill</hi> than <hi>the deſtroying that faith</hi> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>his Apoſtles preached</hi> to the <hi>world;</hi> the <hi>truth</hi> whereof thoſe <hi>Apoſtles ſealed</hi> with their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37590:20"/>
                     <hi>blood,</hi> and for the <hi>defence</hi> of which we ought <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ſummis viribus certare,
<note place="margin">Jude. v. 5.</note> earneſtly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the faith, which was once delivered to the Saints?</hi> Beſides <hi>corruption in Doctrine</hi> is uſually <hi>attended</hi> with <hi>debauchedneſs in converſation. Truth</hi> and <hi>Holineſs ſtand</hi> or <hi>fall</hi> together; ſome <hi>Arch-Hereticks</hi> indeed <hi>ſeemed</hi> very <hi>pious</hi> for a <hi>while, till</hi> their <hi>opinions</hi> met with <hi>conſiderable entertainment. Devotion</hi> like a <hi>Crutch,</hi> muſt <hi>ſupport</hi> them while <hi>weak;</hi> when their <hi>legs</hi> are <hi>ſtrengthened,</hi> they <hi>throw it away.</hi> The <hi>firſt,</hi> and <hi>main oppoſers</hi> of <hi>truth</hi> were known to be <hi>men</hi> of <hi>flagitious lives:</hi> Witneſs the <hi>laſeivious carriage</hi> of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> with his <hi>Helena;</hi> of <hi>Montanus</hi> with his <hi>Priſca</hi> and <hi>Maximilla,</hi> the <hi>ſtrange uncleaneſs</hi> of the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> and the <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable obſcoenity</hi> of the <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> particularly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by <hi>Epiphanius.</hi> And no marvell if our <hi>practices</hi> are <hi>irregular,</hi> when our <hi>Judgements</hi> are <hi>perverted;</hi> if we <hi>turn Gods grace into laſciviouſneſs,</hi> when we come to <hi>deny the Lord that bought us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Look we upon the <hi>foundations</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> and the <hi>derſtoying them</hi> will appear a <hi>manifeſt wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi> God hath <hi>implanted</hi> in mans <hi>nature</hi> an <hi>inclination</hi> to <hi>live ſociably.</hi> Without <hi>laws</hi> there can be <hi>no ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties,</hi> becauſe there can be <hi>nothing of order</hi> and <hi>rule.</hi> He is the <hi>Author</hi> of <hi>power</hi> and <hi>dominion; By me Kings reign</hi> Prov. 18.15. <hi>God ſets</hi> the <hi>Crown</hi> upon a <hi>Princes head,</hi> and <hi>puts</hi> the <hi>Scepter</hi> into <hi>his hand;</hi> to <hi>whom</hi> thus <hi>exalted,</hi> he hath <hi>commanded</hi> our <hi>ſubjection</hi> and <hi>reverence</hi> (<hi>Let every ſoul be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the higher powers,</hi> Rom. 13.1.) and <hi>char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> upon us <hi>a conſcientious obedience</hi> in all things <hi>lawfull: ye muſt needs be ſubject, not only for wrath but alſo for conſcience ſake.</hi> v. 5. ſo that hence it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37590:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>follows; <hi>They who endeavour the ſubverſion of laws or reſiſt the Authority of their Kings,</hi> (whoſe the laws are;) <hi>ſin expreſly againſt the word of God:</hi> Which ſhews the <hi>iniquity</hi> of <hi>deſtroying the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations.</hi> And then no doubt we ſhall ſoon find</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>The miſery, or calamity which attends it:</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed alſo in this <hi>ſuppoſition, if the foundations be deſtroyed.</hi> And truly what can we expect <hi>from ſin,</hi> but <hi>miſery? Hereſies</hi> have done the <hi>Church</hi> more <hi>harm</hi> than <hi>perſecutions.</hi> The <hi>one</hi> hath <hi>ſcratched her face,</hi> but the <hi>other</hi> hath <hi>gnawed her bowels.</hi> The <hi>one</hi> hath ſometimes <hi>put her</hi> into a <hi>feavour,</hi> the <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> hath <hi>preyed</hi> upon her like a <hi>Gangreen:</hi> it is the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> word 2 Tim. 2.17. But among <hi>thoſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs</hi> which are <hi>inſeparable attendants</hi> upon the <hi>prevalency</hi> of <hi>errors,</hi> there is <hi>none more injures Chriſts myſticall body,</hi> than the <hi>ſchiſmes</hi> and <hi>factions</hi> they <hi>directly occaſion. Truth</hi> is the <hi>parent</hi> of <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>concord;</hi> while there is <hi>one faith,</hi> there will be <hi>one ſpirit. Error</hi> is the <hi>unhappy Mother</hi> of <hi>ſtrifes</hi> and <hi>diviſions. Experience</hi> convinceth, that <hi>difference in judgement</hi> will breed <hi>diſtance in affection,</hi> and <hi>diſtance in affection</hi> will interrupt <hi>brotherly Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> As <hi>ſchiſme diſpoſeth</hi> to <hi>Hereſie,</hi> ſo doth <hi>Hereſie</hi> to <hi>ſchiſme:</hi> nor can we imagine there ſhould be <hi>a cloſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e in devotions,</hi> where there <hi>is not an agreement in opinions.</hi> What <hi>grievous confuſions</hi> happened in the Church, when the <hi>Arrians</hi> were <hi>favoured</hi> above the Orthodox? <hi>One</hi> party <hi>ſeparating</hi> from the <hi>other,</hi> and the <hi>fautors</hi> of that <hi>blaſphemy perſecuting</hi> the true <hi>believers</hi> with <hi>unchriſtian cruelty.</hi> I need not mention the <hi>lamentable broyles</hi> which ruined <hi>Germany</hi> by the <hi>rage</hi> of the <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi> Theſe <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities have,</hi> and <hi>do,</hi> and <hi>will</hi> follow, <hi>if the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of doctrine be deſtroyed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:37590:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>And no doubt, the like <hi>evills</hi> muſt be expected upon <hi>deſtroying</hi> the <hi>foundations</hi> of <hi>Government.</hi> It was well ſaid <hi>men had better live where nothing is lawfull, than where all things are:</hi> and <hi>a bramble Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is better than none. Tyranny</hi> makes any <hi>Kingdom</hi> a kind of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> but <hi>Anarchy</hi> makes it a <hi>very Hell:</hi> nay, what if I ſay, even <hi>Hell abhors</hi> it; for that <hi>place of torment</hi> admits of <hi>ſome order,</hi> and there we meet with a <hi>Prince of the Devils.</hi> Take away the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of <hi>Authority,</hi> and you intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>confuſion.</hi> Bring down the <hi>Soveraign power,</hi> and every <hi>Peaſant</hi> will make himſelf <hi>King.</hi> The <hi>ordinary rabble</hi> are ſo <hi>mad-headed,</hi> that if <hi>affairs be</hi> left to their <hi>management, piety,</hi> and <hi>honeſty</hi> will both <hi>ſuffer; Religion</hi> and <hi>juſtice</hi> will be <hi>turned out of doors.</hi> 'Tis not in <hi>vain</hi> the <hi>Scripture</hi> four times repeats, <hi>In thoſe days there was no King in Iſrael:</hi> Since the reaſon of <hi>recording</hi> it ſo often may be gathered from the <hi>places</hi> where it is <hi>found.</hi> When <hi>that people</hi> had <hi>no ſetled Government,</hi> every man was <hi>a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver</hi> to himſelf, and never did they <hi>Commit more wickedneſs,</hi> or <hi>endure more miſery. Micah ſteals</hi> his Mothers <hi>money; part</hi> whereof when reſtored, is made into an <hi>Image,</hi> and the man gets <hi>an houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> of <hi>Gods:</hi> what is the reaſon? <hi>In thoſe days there was no King in Iſrael,</hi> Judg. 17.6. Micahs houſe is <hi>robbed</hi> by the <hi>Danites,</hi> and thoſe Children of Dan <hi>worſhip</hi> this <hi>Image:</hi> How came this <hi>Idolatry? In thoſe days there was no King in Iſrael.</hi> Judg. 18.1. The Levites <hi>Concubine</hi> is <hi>abuſed to death:</hi> when was this <hi>groſs uncleanneſs? In thoſe days when there was no King in Iſrael,</hi> Judg. 19.1. <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin quarrel,</hi> becauſe the <hi>adulterers</hi> eſcape <hi>unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed;</hi> 40000 Iſraelites are <hi>ſlain,</hi> and the <hi>tribe</hi> of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37590:22"/>
                     <hi>Benjamin reduced</hi> to 600, and that <hi>calamity</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded <hi>from the ſame ground: In thoſe days there was no King in Iſrael, every man did that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hich was right in his own eyes.</hi> Judg. 21.25. But what need we <hi>travell</hi> as far as <hi>Canaan,</hi> when <hi>poor England</hi> hath <hi>experienced</hi> theſe <hi>fatall miſchiefs?</hi> It is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the <hi>reach</hi> of our <hi>memories</hi> to recollect ſad <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences</hi> of this <hi>truth.</hi> Our Kingdom <hi>was</hi> once the <hi>wonder of its friends</hi> and the <hi>terror of its ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies:</hi> and ſo <hi>continued,</hi> while <hi>the foundations</hi> were <hi>unſhaken:</hi> but <hi>violent hands</hi> were laid upon <hi>them</hi> by <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>Faction.</hi> A company of <hi>Male-Contents</hi> (like ſo many <hi>Jehues</hi>) <hi>drove</hi> on their <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns</hi> with ſuch <hi>fury,</hi> that the <hi>Sword</hi> prevailed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the <hi>law,</hi> the people (I am <hi>ſorry</hi> to ſay it) were <hi>preached</hi> into <hi>rebellion: Loyall ſubjects</hi> were the <hi>only Malignants,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> could not be <hi>ſerved</hi> if <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> were <hi>obeyed.</hi> How many <hi>lives</hi> and <hi>eſtates</hi> were <hi>ſacrificed</hi> to the <hi>popular fury? Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> fell by thouſands, till at length, that <hi>Incomparable Prince</hi> and <hi>Bleſſed Martyr</hi> laid his <hi>neck</hi> upon the block. —<hi>Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum jubeo renovare dolorem.</hi> The <hi>body</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> had <hi>ſurfeited</hi> of <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>plenty,</hi> and our <hi>ſtate-em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyricks</hi> knew no <hi>cure,</hi> but to <hi>cut off the head.</hi> Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly there were ſome <hi>grievances</hi> to be <hi>redreſſed,</hi> ſome <hi>corruptions</hi> had perhaps <hi>crept</hi> into <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> was this the way to give <hi>eaſe</hi> for the <hi>one,</hi> or to <hi>root</hi> out the <hi>other?</hi> It is ſtrange that the <hi>ſhrinking of a Beam,</hi> or the <hi>jutting of a wall</hi> can no way be <hi>helped</hi> but by <hi>pulling down the houſe?</hi> This is to <hi>avoid</hi> a <hi>leſſer evill</hi> by <hi>admitting</hi> a <hi>ſcore</hi> of <hi>greater.</hi> A <hi>ſcore</hi> did I ſay? that <hi>number</hi> is too <hi>ſmall their name is Legion, for they are many.</hi> So we <hi>found</hi> them, and <hi>groaned</hi> under them for ſeverall years,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37590:22"/>till the Almighty providence <hi>repaired</hi> our <hi>ruines,</hi> and <hi>ſet up</hi> our <hi>pillars</hi> in their <hi>places</hi> again. God grant they may ſtand <hi>firm</hi> againſt all the <hi>attempts</hi> of <hi>dangerous underminers.</hi> But ſince there is a <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of,</hi> an <hi>iniquity</hi> in, and a <hi>miſery followeth</hi> the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying</hi> theſe <hi>foundations,</hi> no marvel if each <hi>pious ſoul bethink</hi> it ſelf of its own <hi>duty,</hi> and often <hi>ask</hi> the <hi>Pſalmiſts queſtion, If the foundations be deſtroyed what can the righteous do?</hi> And ſo I paſs to the <hi>ſecond</hi> generall part of the text;</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>The Interrogation,</hi> which may be looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</p>
                  <p n="1">1. As <hi>vox reflectentis.</hi> The <hi>voice of one ſearching into the true grounds of this dreadfull miſery.</hi> Which ſeems more <hi>probable,</hi> becauſe ſeveral <hi>tranſlations</hi> render it in the <hi>praetertenſe</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſo the <hi>ſeptuagint,</hi> and our <hi>Liturgy-Pſalms, what hath the righteous done? David</hi> was ſatisfied, Gods <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> are <hi>deſerved,</hi> before they be <hi>inflicted.</hi> The <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours</hi> of <hi>ſin</hi> cauſe the <hi>ſhowers</hi> of <hi>ſorrow.
<note place="margin">Lament. 3.33.</note> He doth not afflict willingly, nor grieve the Children of men.</hi> And becauſe we may ſometimes read <hi>malum in malo,</hi> the <hi>evill</hi> we <hi>do</hi> in the <hi>evill</hi> we <hi>ſuffer,</hi> it is worth a ſerious <hi>ſearch</hi> how our <hi>fault</hi> and our <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection ſuite,</hi> that the <hi>Quaery</hi> may be ſoon <hi>reſolved, if the foundations be deſtroyed what the righteous hath done.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Why ſhould not we then who have <hi>ſhared</hi> in the <hi>miſery,</hi> be as <hi>diligent</hi> in the duty? The task will be <hi>eaſie:</hi> For if our <hi>calamities</hi> were <hi>written in blood,</hi> our <hi>ſins</hi> have been <hi>graven with the point of a Diamond. Diſobedience to Authority,</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days,
<note place="margin">1 Kings 18.44.</note> was like the <hi>cloud</hi> ſeen by <hi>Elijahs ſervant, about the bigneſs of a mans hand,</hi> which
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37590:23"/>in <hi>proceſs of time</hi> growing <hi>greater and greater,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11.3.</note> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread</hi> the <hi>face of our heavens:</hi> and <hi>if the clouds be full they will empty themſelves; theſe</hi> did, and in ſo <hi>violent</hi> a manner, as to <hi>beat down</hi> all before them. Little <hi>ſhelter</hi> could be found from that <hi>ſtorm.</hi> Nor could it be otherwiſe imagined, when our <hi>own hands</hi> by <hi>uncovering the houſe</hi> had <hi>expoſed</hi> it to the <hi>weather,</hi> well might the <hi>poſts</hi> be <hi>rotted,</hi> and the <hi>building fall.</hi> And when we have thus <hi>enquired</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>cauſe,</hi> how can we <hi>reflect</hi> upon it without <hi>aking hearts,</hi> and <hi>moiſtened eyes, bewailing</hi> our <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, ſinfulneſs,</hi> and <hi>imprudence;</hi> which leads me to the <hi>ſecond</hi> notion</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As <hi>vox deplorantis, the voice of a Mourner.</hi> And this will <hi>agree</hi> with <hi>both Tranſlations.</hi> With the <hi>old, what hath the righteous done?</hi> ſo it is <hi>vox de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorantis peccaium:</hi> with the <hi>new what can the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous do?</hi> ſo it is <hi>vox deplorantis impotentiam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Vox deplorantis peccatum, a Lamentation for the ſin.</hi> The <hi>beſt grieving</hi> for the <hi>afflictions of Joſeph,</hi> is <hi>firſt</hi> to <hi>grieve</hi> for <hi>the ſins of Joſeph.</hi> Men can never be truly <hi>affected</hi> with their <hi>puniſhments,</hi> till they be rightly <hi>apprehenſive</hi> of their <hi>wickedneſs.</hi> And ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the <hi>phraſe,</hi> it is <hi>what hath the righteous done?</hi> not <hi>what hath the righteous ſuffered?</hi> To convince us, the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> had an <hi>eye</hi> at the <hi>malum culpae,</hi> as well as the <hi>malum paenae;</hi> that he <hi>wept</hi> for the <hi>crime committed,</hi> as well as for the <hi>miſery inflicted.</hi> In theſe terms the Scripture expreſſeth our <hi>peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiall mourning: no man repented him of his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſaying what have I done?</hi> Jerem. 8.6. And ſure while we <hi>know not</hi> our ſins, ſo as to be <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,</hi> while we <hi>underſtand not</hi> our <hi>tranſgreſſions,</hi> ſo as to be <hi>ſorry</hi> for them; well may we fear that all
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37590:23"/>the <hi>foundations of the earth will be moved out of courſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This alſo inſtructs us in a neceſſary <hi>duty.</hi> That whenſoever the <hi>foundations</hi> are in danger to be <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed,</hi> inſtead of <hi>perſiſting</hi> in thoſe <hi>enormous crimes</hi> which may cauſe their <hi>utter downfall;</hi> we ſhould rather ſadly <hi>lament</hi> our <hi>ſins</hi> already <hi>committed,</hi> whereby God is <hi>provoked</hi> ſo dreadfully to appear againſt us. And oh! that <hi>our heads were waters, and our eyes a fountain of tears,</hi> that we might <hi>weep</hi> day and night, for thoſe <hi>errors, ſchiſmes, factions, ſecular deſigns,</hi> and <hi>ſeditious practices,</hi> whereby the <hi>pillars</hi> of this nation have been made to <hi>reell,</hi> and the <hi>props</hi> both of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>ſtate</hi> ſo terribly <hi>ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 79.3.</note> And <hi>happy</hi> may we think our ſelves thus to <hi>waſh</hi> away the <hi>ſtain of that blood, which hath been ſhed like water about our Jeruſalem.</hi> Whereas if we go on without <hi>remorſe,</hi> if there be no <hi>relentings</hi> in our <hi>bowels,</hi> no <hi>expreſſions of ſorrow</hi> in our <hi>outward carriage,</hi> we ſhall find our <hi>miſeries encreaſed</hi> to that <hi>height,</hi> as to render us altogether <hi>helpleſs:</hi> for <hi>if the foundations be deſtroyed, what can the righteous do?</hi> and in that reading, the <hi>queſtion</hi> is</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Vox deplorantis impotentiam, a lamentation of our inability to help our ſelves. Miſeries</hi> are much ſooner <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned</hi> than <hi>removed.</hi> It is in <hi>our power</hi> to <hi>bring</hi> them God only can <hi>withdraw</hi> them. A <hi>ſtately fabrick</hi> is eaſily <hi>demoliſhed,</hi> but <hi>care</hi> and <hi>skill</hi> muſt both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to its <hi>reedification.</hi> A <hi>pernicious Heretick</hi> may <hi>deſtroy</hi> the <hi>foundations of doctrine;</hi> A <hi>ſeditious Rebel</hi> may <hi>ſhake</hi> the <hi>foundations of Government:</hi> but when theſe wicked <hi>pranks</hi> are <hi>played,</hi> 'tis hard to <hi>eſtabliſh</hi> them again. So little muſt we look to <hi>our ſelves,</hi> and ſo much to <hi>God,</hi> acknowledgeing his <hi>help</hi> alone in our <hi>petitions</hi> for it with David, Pſ. 60.11.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37590:24"/>
                     <hi>Give us help from trouble, for vain is the help of man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if ever the world be engaged to <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> this <hi>truth,</hi> Englands <hi>hand</hi> muſt go with the firſt. How <hi>deſperate</hi> a <hi>condition</hi> we were in, our ſelves can give the beſt <hi>account: torn</hi> with continuall <hi>experience</hi> of running <hi>from bad to worſe,</hi> become the <hi>reproach</hi> of thoſe who <hi>hated,</hi> and the <hi>pity</hi> of thoſe who <hi>loved</hi> us. Nor did the <hi>wiſeſt</hi> know what <hi>courſe</hi> to <hi>ſteer,</hi> till an <hi>over-ruling providence</hi> ſet all things <hi>right,</hi> reducing us both for <hi>doctrine</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> to our <hi>ancient happineſs.</hi> The bleſſed <hi>reſtauration</hi> of our <hi>Soveraign,</hi> and in him of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> made all perſons (howſoever <hi>diſſatisfied</hi> in point of <hi>intereſt</hi>) acknowledge a <hi>digitus Dei,</hi> that the <hi>finger of God</hi> was in it. Never were people redeemed from <hi>ſlavery</hi> with a more <hi>omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent hand.</hi> Never had nation more <hi>cauſe</hi> to ſay <hi>this was the Lords doing.</hi> However we <hi>forget,</hi> poſterity will <hi>remember</hi> it, and (I hope) <hi>redeem</hi> with <hi>thankfulneſs</hi> what we have <hi>forfeited</hi> by <hi>ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</hi> And for <hi>our ſelves,</hi> ſuppoſing our <hi>deſerved Judgements</hi> fall upon our heads, if according to our <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merits,</hi> the <hi>foundations</hi> ſhould <hi>be,</hi> or <hi>near</hi> to be <hi>deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> let us at laſt be <hi>wiſe,</hi> and look upon this <hi>queſtion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. As <hi>voxin quirentis, an enquiry what we</hi> are to do in ſuch an extremity. And ſo we take it direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according to our <hi>own tranſlation, what can the righteous do?</hi> If <hi>calamitous miſeries</hi> may not be <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented,</hi> it is <hi>prudence</hi> to conſider how we ſhould <hi>bear up</hi> under them, that they may neither <hi>cruſh our backs,</hi> nor <hi>break our bearts:</hi> that by an <hi>holy poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> we may at preſent <hi>alleviate</hi> our <hi>burden,</hi> and in Gods good time, <hi>obtain</hi> a <hi>Gracious relieaſe</hi> from it. And methink the <hi>next words</hi> direct us to an
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37590:24"/>
                     <hi>excellent expedient</hi> for this work. Immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the queſtion, <hi>what can the righteous do?</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes (as if the Pſalmiſt made <hi>anſwer</hi> to himſelf) <hi>The Lord is in his Holy Temple, the Lords throne is in Heaven</hi> v. 4. wherein is inſinuated our duty of <hi>fiduciall waiting upon,</hi> and <hi>ſupplicating God for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs from thoſe grievances. A fiduciall waiting upon him. In the Lord put I my truſt</hi> v. 1. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the <hi>wicked contrivacnes of men,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the <hi>malicious deſigns</hi> wherein they are <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged;</hi> yet ſince <hi>Gods over-ruling power</hi> can <hi>diſappoint</hi> their <hi>purpoſes,</hi> it is beſt for us to <hi>confide in,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 131.3.</note> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie upon</hi> Him. Thus <hi>let Iſrael hope in the Lord from benceforth, and for ever.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 46.1.2.</note> And then he will be <hi>our refuge and ſtrength, a very preſent help in trouble:</hi> ſo that we need <hi>not fear though the earth be removed, and though the Mountains be carried into the midſt of the Sea.</hi> But our <hi>fiduciall waiting</hi> muſt be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with <hi>fervent ſupplications. The Lord is good to them that wait for him, to the ſoul that ſeeketh him</hi> Lament. 3.26. and <hi>ſeeking</hi> in Scripture is as much as <hi>praying.</hi> To him therefore muſt we <hi>lift</hi> up our <hi>hands</hi> and <hi>hearts,</hi> devoutly <hi>bewailing</hi> thoſe <hi>ſins</hi> which have proved an <hi>inlet</hi> to our <hi>diſtreſſes,</hi> and humbly <hi>imploring</hi> his <hi>gracious favour</hi> to vouchſafe us a <hi>joyfull deliverance</hi> from them.</p>
                  <p>And when we have paid theſe <hi>duties</hi> to the <hi>God of heaven,</hi> our <hi>next ſervice</hi> muſt be to the <hi>Gods up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth:</hi> thoſe who are appointed his <hi>Vice-gerents,</hi> and <hi>deputed</hi> to rule <hi>for</hi> and <hi>under</hi> Him. It is <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glands</hi> happineſs to enjoy a <hi>gracious King;</hi> ſo <hi>exact a modell of Government</hi> as <hi>few</hi> if any <hi>nation</hi> in the world can <hi>parallel;</hi> ſuch <hi>wholſome laws</hi> as (if duly <hi>obſerved</hi>) would <hi>prevent,</hi> and (if vigorouſly <hi>executed</hi>)
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37590:25"/>would <hi>puniſh</hi> all manner of <hi>wickedneſs.</hi> Nor wants <hi>ſhe</hi> a <hi>Benjamins portion</hi> of <hi>ſpirituall bleſſings.</hi> She glories in a <hi>Church</hi> (<hi>maugre</hi> the <hi>ſpitefull tongues</hi> of her adverſaries) <hi>reformed</hi> according to the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-Canon,</hi> and <hi>pattern</hi> of the <hi>pureſt times:</hi> the <hi>doctrines</hi> of the Goſpell ſincerely <hi>preached,</hi> and the <hi>three Orders</hi> ſo celebrated by <hi>Antiquity, maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> againſt the <hi>humour</hi> of our <hi>factious Levellers.</hi> On theſe <hi>foundations, Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> are <hi>built,</hi> but <hi>if the foundations be deſtroyed, what can the righteous do?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> you who are <hi>entruſted</hi> by his <hi>ſacred Majeſty</hi> to manage the <hi>important af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs</hi> of this <hi>County; You</hi> who <hi>repreſent</hi> the perſon of your <hi>Soveraign;</hi> On <hi>you</hi> muſt we <hi>relie,</hi> and to <hi>you</hi> do we make our <hi>earneſt addreſſes,</hi> that by <hi>your vigilant care, prudent counſells, authoritative com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,</hi> and <hi>impartiall juſtice</hi> the <hi>threatening deſtruction</hi> of our <hi>foundations</hi> may be <hi>hindred.</hi> I ſay, the <hi>threatening deſtruction.</hi> For what man ſees not the <hi>danger</hi> we are in The <hi>prevalency</hi> of <hi>Atheiſme, Blaſphemy, Prophaneſs;</hi> the <hi>Wild errors, and Hereticall opinions</hi> which <hi>openly</hi> ſhew themſelves abroad, bidding <hi>defiance</hi> to whatſoever is <hi>religious;</hi> work in us a <hi>dreadfull apprehenſion</hi> that our <hi>foundations of doctrine</hi> are ready to <hi>fall.</hi> The <hi>viſible contempt</hi> of known <hi>laws;</hi> a <hi>ſtubborn oppoſition</hi> to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mauds both of <hi>Givill</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Governours;</hi> the <hi>keeping</hi> up of <hi>factions;</hi> the <hi>principles of rebellion</hi> imbibed in our <hi>unhappy times,</hi> and not ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>rooted</hi> out of mens hearts; the ſe t ng up <hi>altar</hi> againſt <hi>altar; barns</hi> againſt <hi>Churches; new models of worſhip</hi> to croſs the <hi>preſribed form:</hi> put us in <hi>fear</hi> that the <hi>foundations of Government</hi> are in a <hi>tottering
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37590:25"/>condition.</hi> For had theſe things <hi>no relation</hi> to <hi>Religion,</hi> yet as <hi>thwartings</hi> of the <hi>Civil power</hi> they muſt needs <hi>bode miſchief</hi> to the King and Kingdom. Yet though theſe <hi>Pillars</hi> be ſo ſhrewdly <hi>ſhaken, your</hi> ſeaſonable aſſiſtance may not only <hi>ſecure</hi> them from quite <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> but alſo <hi>eſtabliſh</hi> them <hi>firm</hi> and <hi>unmoveable.</hi> Let but men be <hi>throughly diſcouraged</hi> when they <hi>offend</hi> in this nature; let them but a little <hi>feel</hi> your <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity,</hi> who have thus long <hi>contemned</hi> your <hi>clemency;</hi> and they will either be <hi>reduced</hi> into <hi>good order,</hi> or however become <hi>leſs irregular.</hi> It is poſſible my words may be accuſed of <hi>cruelty;</hi> ſure there is no <hi>reaſon</hi> for it. We judge it <hi>prudence,</hi> if a <hi>fire</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen rather to <hi>uncover the roof, to throw away the tiles,</hi> and <hi>break down ſome</hi> of the <hi>rafiers,</hi> than ſuffer the <hi>houſe to be burnt</hi> to the ground. And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is better that ſome <hi>particular</hi> men (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when <hi>refractory</hi> and <hi>contumacious</hi>) be <hi>curbed</hi> by thoſe <hi>penalties</hi> which <hi>laws</hi> have provided, than an <hi>whole Kingdom</hi> ſhould either become a <hi>neſt of Hereſies,</hi> or <hi>a field of blood.</hi> But my <hi>zeal</hi> may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps make me <hi>preſumptuous</hi> in offering to <hi>preſcribe</hi> to <hi>your Lordſhips</hi> or <hi>theſe Gentlemen.</hi> It is time to have done, and I end all with this <hi>prayer. God Almighty direct and guide you and all concerned in the publick affairs before you, to</hi> His own Glory, the Kings Honour, the Kingdoms happineſs, <hi>the ſettling us upon thoſe firm</hi> foundations <hi>of</hi> truth and peace;
<note place="margin">Iſai. 63.7.</note> 
                     <hi>that we who are members of the Engliſh Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> may ſee it a praiſe in the whole earth, <hi>and after we have</hi> ſerved our Generations may be admitted into the new Jeruſalem,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.10.</note> that City which hath foundations, whoſe builder and maker is God: <hi>there to reign in everlaſting glory, through Jeſus
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37590:26"/>Chriſt our Lord.</hi> To whom with the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> be <hi>Honour, Praiſe, Dominion,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> henceforth and for evermore. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:37590:26"/>
                  <p>CAESARS DUE Honour. A SERMON Preached at St. <hi>Martins</hi> Church in <hi>Leiceſter, May,</hi> 29. 1669. before the Mayor and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Tho. Stanhope A.M.</hi> Vicar of St. <hi>Margarets</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:37590:27"/>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:37590:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>CAESARS DUE Honour.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 Peter 2.17.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>Honour the King.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe <hi>few</hi> words conclude the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> appointed for this <hi>Solemnity;</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> having <hi>choſen</hi> them for the occaſion, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be <hi>ſuitable</hi> for a <hi>diſcourſe</hi> upon it. The <hi>Day</hi> we celebrate in remembrance of thoſe ſignal bleſſings it hath brought to us in a <hi>King,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">29. <hi>May,</hi> 1630.</note> as he was <hi>natus</hi> and <hi>renatus</hi> upon it, <hi>born</hi> into the World,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37590:28"/>and <hi>reborn</hi> to his Kingdom;
<note place="margin">29. <hi>May,</hi> 1660.</note> whereunto though he had a <hi>right</hi> before, yet after a compelled <hi>exile,</hi> now <hi>nine years ago</hi> he took <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of his Royal Palace. And in the midſt of our <hi>rejoycing</hi> for him, it is but fit we ſhould learn our <hi>duty</hi> to him, which the Apoſtle hath ſhortly ſummed up in the Word <hi>Honour. Honour the King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>At the 13. verſe of this Chapter is propounded a due <hi>Chriſtian carriage</hi> towards <hi>Magiſtrates:</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably enough there ſet down for ſome <hi>extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary</hi> reaſon. It ſeems thoſe <hi>early dayes</hi> of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity were <hi>tainted</hi> with the ſtrange <hi>error</hi> that <hi>a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Subjection to Authority could not conſiſt with, but was an abridgement of our Goſpel liberty.</hi> This is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated verſe 16. <hi>As free, and not uſing your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty for a cloak of maliciouſneſs, but as the ſervants of God.</hi> A <hi>freedome</hi> indeed is <hi>granted,</hi> but then that freedom muſt be <hi>rightly uſed:</hi> not to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage <hi>ſedition,</hi> or <hi>diſ-obedience,</hi> to make it <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>a cloak</hi> of maliciouſneſs, to cover <hi>faction, ambition, ſiniſter deſigns,</hi> or any thing of that nature: but that men ſhould <hi>duly</hi> and <hi>rightly uſe it,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>as the ſervants of God.</hi> Upon the mention of which Word, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> (as it were) <hi>recapitulates,</hi> and drawes the <hi>whole ſervice</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>narrow compaſs,</hi> verſe 17. With relation to four <hi>Objects</hi> thereof. 1. <hi>Mankind in general: Honour all men.</hi> 2. <hi>Chriſtians in particular: Love the brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</hi> 3. <hi>God as the principal: Fear God.</hi> 4. <hi>Our Prince, as immediately under him. Honour the King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It may not be amiſs to draw ſome few <hi>obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> from the <hi>placing theſe two laſt together,</hi> which ſhall onely be done in a <hi>few</hi> words before I fix up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:37590:28"/>my <hi>main Subject.</hi> And here let us note</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>1</label> That <hi>the ſame infallible Spirit which hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> a duty <hi>to be owing unto</hi> God, <hi>hath likewiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared</hi> a duty <hi>to be owing to our</hi> King. That very <hi>Scripture,</hi> nay that very <hi>verſe</hi> which calls upon us to <hi>fear God,</hi> cals upon us alſo to <hi>honour the King.</hi> It is a <hi>groſs miſtake</hi> if we <hi>fancy</hi> our ſelves any more at <hi>freedome</hi> from the <hi>one</hi> than we are from the <hi>other.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>2</label>
                     <hi>The ſame infallible Spirit which hath declared</hi> the duty <hi>owing unto</hi> God, and the duty <hi>owing to the</hi> King, <hi>hath</hi> linked <hi>theſe two duties</hi> together. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>between</hi> to <hi>part</hi> them, but as ſoon as the <hi>one</hi> is delivered the <hi>other</hi> follows: <hi>Fear God, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the King.</hi> Nay, as if this were not ſufficient, <hi>Solomon connects</hi> them <hi>together</hi> with a copulative Particle, Prov. 24.21. <hi>My Son fear thou the Lord, and the King.</hi> Now, <hi>Quae Deus conjunxit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>What God hath joyned together let no man put aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> In <hi>vain</hi> do we think ever to be <hi>truly pious</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>God,</hi> till we be <hi>truly loyal</hi> to our <hi>King,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>3</label>
                     <hi>The ſame infallible Spirit which hath in</hi> a large comprehenſive word, <hi>declared</hi> the duty <hi>we ow unto</hi> God, <hi>hath in</hi> a like comprehenſive word <hi>declared</hi> the duty <hi>we owe unto the</hi> King. That our <hi>returns</hi> to <hi>neither</hi> of them may be <hi>narrow</hi> and <hi>ſcant. Fear</hi> hath ſometimes that <hi>full</hi> ſignification to include <hi>all acts of piety. This do and live, for I fear God,</hi> Gen. 42.18. <hi>Honour</hi> ſo <hi>large</hi> an acceptation, as to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend <hi>all ſervice and duty. Honour thy Father and thy Mother,</hi> Exod. 20.12. Now as the <hi>firſt</hi> of theſe is <hi>uſed</hi> here with reſpect to <hi>the Lord, Fear God:</hi> ſo the <hi>latter</hi> with reſpect to <hi>our Soveraign, Honour the King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:37590:29"/>
                  <p>In which Words there are two parts. 1. <hi>The Act, Honour.</hi> 2. <hi>The Object, the King:</hi> both which with a conſideration of the <hi>perſons</hi> to whom this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> was written, viz. <hi>the believing Jewes converted to Chriſtianity,</hi> make it plain that the <hi>duty</hi> hath relation to us, as <hi>a Chriſtian precept,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by <hi>Chriſts Apoſtle,</hi> to thoſe who were then <hi>Chriſts followers:</hi> and ſo <hi>we</hi> alſo ſtand <hi>engaged</hi> to <hi>Honour the King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A <hi>truth</hi> which will appear as if written with <hi>a Sun beam,</hi> when we have enquired into the <hi>nature of this Honour,</hi> and <hi>the grounds</hi> whereupon <hi>it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for.</hi> In the diſpatch whereof (for <hi>methods</hi> ſake) becauſe the word <hi>Honour</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and admits of <hi>ſeveral ſignifications,</hi> under <hi>each</hi> of them I ſhall <hi>ſubjoyn the reaſons</hi> for it, <hi>warranted</hi> by <hi>Scripture,</hi> whence we have the <hi>beſt direction</hi> for our duty: and <hi>confirmed</hi> by the <hi>teſtimony</hi> of <hi>the Primitive Fathers,</hi> who were <hi>likelieſt</hi> to know the <hi>meaning</hi> of ſuch <hi>commands</hi> in Scripture: to let the World ſee that we <hi>exact no more</hi> of men, for our <hi>Chriſtian Princes,</hi> than they were willing to <hi>afford</hi> the very <hi>Heathen Emperors.</hi> And when it appears the <hi>duties</hi> we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire to <hi>be paid them</hi> are <hi>challenged</hi> by the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and the <hi>Doctrine of the Ancient Church;</hi> let any <hi>ſober</hi> man judge whether <hi>we</hi> be <hi>blame-worthy</hi> for <hi>preaching,</hi> or <hi>others</hi> for <hi>refuſing</hi> to <hi>practice</hi> them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt</hi> then, for the <hi>Nature of this Honour.</hi> It is (as I ſaid) a word of <hi>large extent,</hi> and <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>vines bring</hi> all under three <hi>Heads.</hi> 1. <hi>Honor in corde.</hi> 2. <hi>Honor in ore.</hi> 3. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nor in opere. Honour in the heart. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the tongue. Honour in the Act.</hi> And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this <hi>diſtribution,</hi> I ſhall <hi>here</hi> take notice of it,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:37590:29"/>for there is <hi>no one</hi> of theſe <hi>three</hi> but a <hi>Prince</hi> may <hi>claim</hi> it as his <hi>due.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Honor in corde, Honour in the heart,</hi> by which is meant <hi>a reverent eſtimation of the perſon to whom it is born.</hi> Thus the word is uſed by the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> Rom. 12.10. <hi>in honour preferring one another.</hi> And thus we are called to <hi>give</hi> it unto <hi>Kings,</hi> Rom. 13.7. <hi>Render therefore to all their dues, tribute to whom tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute is due, cuſtome to whom cuſtome, fear to whom fear, honour to whom honour;</hi> the putting <hi>theſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</hi> as well as the <hi>diſcourſe foregoing,</hi> ſhewes the <hi>Supream Magiſtrate</hi> is here <hi>intended. Mean</hi> and <hi>low thoughts</hi> are not <hi>fit</hi> to be <hi>entertained</hi> of thoſe who are exerciſed in <hi>high employments.</hi> Whom <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>raiſed</hi> in the World, <hi>thoſe</hi> ſhould we <hi>raiſe</hi> in our <hi>eſteem. This</hi> indeed ought to be <hi>the fountain</hi> whence all <hi>other duties</hi> flow; the <hi>foundation</hi> whereon the reſt of our <hi>ſervices</hi> are <hi>built:</hi> for without an <hi>bearty value</hi> for them, none of our <hi>outward performances</hi> will be <hi>ſincere</hi> towards them. Nay, ſuppoſe God ſhould <hi>at any time ſet</hi> over us ſuch a <hi>King,</hi> as is a <hi>wicked man,</hi> we muſt look upon his <hi>publick ſtation</hi> abſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from his <hi>perſonal faults. David</hi> owns <hi>Saul</hi> for <hi>Gods Anointed,</hi> and payes <hi>him</hi> a <hi>reverence</hi> accordingly. Chriſt ſhewes no <hi>diſ-reſpect</hi> either to <hi>Pilate,</hi> or <hi>Herod</hi> Their <hi>failing</hi> in <hi>not honouring God,</hi> is no <hi>warrant</hi> for us to <hi>fail</hi> by <hi>not honouring them. Puniſhed they</hi> ſhall be for the <hi>one,</hi> and <hi>puniſhed we</hi> ſhall be (if <hi>faulty</hi>) for the <hi>other.</hi> And certainly this is plain enough from the <hi>Text.</hi> For this <hi>direction</hi> given to theſe <hi>Chriſtian converts</hi> of <hi>honour ing the King,</hi> had either relation to <hi>Claudius</hi> or <hi>Nero;</hi> &amp; the <hi>better</hi> of them was a man <hi>bad</hi> enough. This then is the <hi>firſt</hi> kind of <hi>honour:</hi> and there are two <hi>reaſons,</hi> why it ſhould be paid to <hi>all Kings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:37590:30"/>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe of <hi>thoſe honourable titles which God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath given them,</hi> Perſons who have <hi>titles of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> conferred upon them by <hi>earthly Princes</hi> chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge an <hi>eſteem proportionable</hi> thereunto: how much more <hi>they</hi> who have <hi>theſe</hi> from <hi>God?</hi> Where he affords his <hi>marks of honour,</hi> there ſhould we yield our <hi>teſtimonies of honour,</hi> as <hi>cloſing</hi> with his <hi>diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and making his <hi>providence</hi> in <hi>diſpoſal</hi> of the <hi>one,</hi> our <hi>rule</hi> for a <hi>diſpoſal</hi> of the <hi>other.</hi> Among thoſe <hi>titles</hi> I ſhall name no more than that of <hi>Gods,</hi> Pſal. 82.6. <hi>I have ſaid ye are Gods.</hi> It is true, that <hi>name</hi> doth point at <hi>their</hi> duty, that <hi>as Gods</hi> they ſhould <hi>excel</hi> in <hi>holineſs,</hi> in <hi>juſtice,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>vertues;</hi> not <hi>fearing the face of men,</hi> or <hi>conſulting onely their intereſt with men;</hi> but withal it <hi>points</hi> at <hi>our</hi> duty, that we ſhould <hi>honour them as</hi> we <hi>honour God:</hi> Not by <hi>ſacrificing</hi> or performing any <hi>divine worſhip</hi> to them; (after the <hi>Idolatrous cuſtom</hi> of the <hi>Heathens</hi>) no, nor by <hi>yielding</hi> them <hi>an unlimited obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience;</hi> (as will appear <hi>hereafter</hi>) but by <hi>affording</hi> them a <hi>real</hi> and <hi>high eſteem</hi> in our <hi>hearts:</hi> to ſhew, that as we are bound to <hi>entertain</hi> no <hi>thoughts</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> but ſuch as are <hi>ſuitable</hi> to his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> ſo no <hi>thoughts</hi> of <hi>them,</hi> but <hi>ſuch</hi> as are <hi>agreeable</hi> to their <hi>quality.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe of <hi>the honourable place wherein God hath ſet them,</hi> He hath made them <hi>caput populi,</hi> the <hi>head of the people:</hi> and as all the <hi>members honour</hi> the <hi>head,</hi> ſo ſhould we <hi>honour them.</hi> They are his <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Vice-gerents; à quo ſunt ſecundi, poſt quem primi, ante omnes &amp; ſuper omnes Deos,</hi> in <hi>Tertullians</hi> phraſe: the <hi>very next to him</hi> before <hi>all, and</hi> above <hi>all feigned Deities.</hi> Now as the <hi>nearer</hi> any perſon is to the <hi>King</hi> the <hi>greater honour</hi> he may <hi>claim:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apolog. cap.</hi> 30.</note> ſo the <hi>nearer</hi> the <hi>King</hi> is to <hi>God,</hi> the more <hi>honour</hi> doth <hi>his place confer</hi>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:37590:30"/>upon him. <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> is not only <hi>Gods ordinance,</hi> but <hi>particular Magiſtrates</hi> are of his <hi>appointing. Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cometh neither from the Eaſt, nor from the Weſt, nor from the South: but God is the Judge, he putteth down one and ſetteth up another,</hi> Pſal. 75.6, 7. And this I am ſure was the <hi>ſence</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Church.</hi> Witneſs <hi>Theophilus</hi> of <hi>Antioch</hi> about 170 years after Chriſt: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Autolycum pag.</hi> 76. <hi>Edit. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>The King indeed is not a God, but he is a man appointed to his office under God. Irenaeus</hi> about ten years <hi>after</hi> him. <hi>Cujus juſſu homines naſcuntur, ejus &amp; juſſu Reges conſtituuntur.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Adv. Haereſes lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 20.</note> By whoſe word men are born, by his word</hi> Kings are appointed. We have ſeen <hi>two plain teſtimonies</hi> for the <hi>Greek,</hi> let us ſee <hi>two</hi> more for the <hi>Latine Church.</hi> One is from <hi>Tertullian,</hi> about 200 Years after Chriſt.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apol. cap.</hi> 30.</note> 
                     <hi>Inde eſt Imperator, unde &amp; homo antequàm Imperator. Inde poteſtas illi, unde &amp; ſpiritus. The ſame God who made the man,</hi> makes the Emperour. <hi>Thence hath he his power, whence he receives his ſoul.</hi> And as if that had not been <hi>enough,</hi> he goes on more <hi>fully. It is neceſſary we look upon the Emperour — ut eum, quem Dominus noſter elegit,</hi> &amp;c. as <hi>the perſon,</hi> whom our Lord hath choſen: So as I may well ſay,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Noſter eſt magis Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar ut a Deo noſtro conſtitutus Apol. cap.</hi> 33.</note> 
                     <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar is the more Ours becauſe</hi> appointed by our God. To him I adde St. <hi>Auſtin,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. de Civit. Dei lib.</hi> 4 <hi>cap.</hi> 33.</note> Deus terrenum regnum &amp; piis &amp; impiis dat ſicut ei placet,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>God accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his own pleaſure, diſpoſeth of earthly power to the righteous, and to the wicked.
<note n="†" place="margin">
                           <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 21.</note> He</hi> that <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted Marius,</hi> did likewiſe promote <hi>Caeſar: He</hi> that gave the <hi>Scepter</hi> to <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> gave it to <hi>Nero: He</hi> who committed the <hi>Empire</hi> to <hi>both Veſpaſians,</hi> committed it alſo to <hi>Domitian:</hi> and <hi>He</hi> who <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted Conſtantine</hi> the <hi>Chriſtian, exalted Julian the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:37590:31"/>Apoſtate.</hi> If this <hi>doctrine</hi> be not <hi>embraced now,</hi> it is a ſign men are <hi>fallen</hi> from what was <hi>admitted before.</hi> Nor is it onely the doctrine of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> but <hi>theirs</hi> becauſe the <hi>doctrine of the Scripture.</hi> Chriſt <hi>owns Pilates power,</hi> to be from <hi>heaven: Thou couldſt have no power againſt me, unleſs it were</hi> given thee from above, John 19.11. and St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Roman Emperors, The powers that be are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God,</hi> Rom. 13.1. <hi>One</hi> thing more before I leave this Point. If the <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Fathers</hi> own this <hi>deſignation of Princes by God,</hi> how <hi>horrid</hi> is the <hi>inſolency</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who would <hi>ſubject</hi> Kings to their <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and make <hi>their ſwords ſtoop to his Keyes?</hi> And on the other ſide, how <hi>abhominable</hi> is the <hi>wickedneſs</hi> of ſome <hi>pretended Proteſtants,</hi> who would ſet up the <hi>power of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> above the <hi>King?</hi> What <hi>followed</hi> thereupon we cannot but <hi>remember;</hi> and to <hi>terrifie</hi> us from the <hi>like</hi> hereafter, God grant it may <hi>never</hi> be <hi>forgotten.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The ſecond ſort of Honour is <hi>Honor in Ore, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the Tongue.</hi> We are to employ our <hi>Tongues</hi> for them, <hi>ſpeaking good</hi> of, and <hi>beſpeaking good</hi> for them; which <hi>laſt</hi> is beſt done by <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> to God. It is the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> charge, that <hi>firſt of all, ſupplications, and prayers, interceſſions, and giving of thanks be made for all men. For Kings, and for all that are in Authority,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.1, 2. And ſure this <hi>charge</hi> was never more <hi>obſerved</hi> by any <hi>Church: Each</hi> of our <hi>conſtant Litugy ſervices</hi> having a <hi>prayer</hi> for the <hi>King</hi> in it. Nor can it be denied, but this was a <hi>duty</hi> payd by the <hi>ancient Chriſtians.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Autolicum pag.</hi> 76. <hi>Edit. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell.</hi>
                     </note> I appeal to <hi>Theophilus</hi> mentioned before, <hi>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. I will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the King, not by affording him any divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:37590:31"/>(that they <hi>decryed</hi> in the <hi>Heathens</hi>) <hi>but by praying for him.</hi> And <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaks <hi>fully</hi> in the Name of <hi>all.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Apolog.</hi> cap. 30.</note> Precati ſumus omnes ſemper pro omnibus Imperatoribus. We</hi> all <hi>of us do</hi> always <hi>pray for all our Emperors:</hi> delivering there the <hi>matter</hi> of their prayers, a <hi>long life,</hi> a <hi>ſafe Kingdom,</hi> a <hi>quiet houſe, valiant Armies, faithfull councells, honeſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> a <hi>peaceable world:</hi> And as if theſe had not been <hi>good wiſhes enough,</hi> he adds, <hi>Quaecunque homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis &amp; Caeſaris vota ſunt. Whatſoever he can farther deſire, either as Man or Emperor.</hi> And ſure if this were a piece of <hi>ſervice due</hi> from <hi>them,</hi> it is no leſs <hi>due</hi> from <hi>us,</hi> and from <hi>both</hi> upon a threefold account 2 <hi>ex parte Dei,</hi> 3 <hi>ex parte noſtri,</hi> 3 <hi>ex par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſui.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Ex parte Dei.</hi> A reaſon there is for it <hi>on</hi> Gods part, as it is <hi>a thing wherein he takes pleaſure. For this is good and acceptable in the ſight of God our Saviour,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.3. The <hi>command</hi> before had <hi>teſtified</hi> his <hi>good-liking,</hi> this <hi>motive</hi> further <hi>argues</hi> his <hi>approbation.</hi> Hereby we own <hi>him</hi> as the <hi>fountain</hi> of all <hi>bleſſings.</hi> When the moſt <hi>potent</hi> perſons up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth are not <hi>relied</hi> upon, but God Almighty <hi>invocated</hi> for them; <hi>He</hi> deſired to <hi>guide, protect,</hi> and <hi>preſerve</hi> them: the <hi>greateſt glory</hi> muſt <hi>redound</hi> to him, his <hi>Soveraignty</hi> being <hi>acknowledged over them</hi> as <hi>theirs</hi> is <hi>over us.</hi> And ſurely this delights him much more than the <hi>calumniating, reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> or <hi>raking</hi> into any <hi>faults</hi> whereof they may be <hi>guilty.</hi> That <hi>man after Gods own heart,</hi> holy <hi>David</hi> knew well what would <hi>pleaſe</hi> him, and therefore in compoſing a <hi>Pſalm</hi> for <hi>Solomon</hi> next to <hi>ſucceed</hi> in the <hi>Throne,</hi> he <hi>begins</hi> it with that <hi>excellent petition</hi> (to acquaint us with our duty)
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:37590:32"/>
                     <hi>Give the King thy Judgements O Lord, and thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs unto the Kings Son,</hi> Pſal. 72.1.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>reaſonableneſs</hi> hereof appears <hi>Ex parte noſtri,</hi> with <hi>respect to our ſelves:</hi> becauſe it is a thing which <hi>leads to our own advantage.</hi> This we have alſo from the Apoſtle: That <hi>under them we may lead quiet and peaceable lives in all godlineſs and honeſty.</hi> The <hi>bleſſings</hi> which <hi>Princes</hi> receive tend to the <hi>peoples good.</hi> They are <hi>cuſtodes utriuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> tabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae,</hi> and the <hi>better</hi> each of the <hi>tables</hi> is kept, the more is the <hi>Subjects benefit.</hi> What can we deſire but the <hi>eſtabliſhment</hi> of <hi>holineſs</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſs?</hi> that <hi>God</hi> may be <hi>ſerved</hi> and <hi>morall duties may be obſerved:</hi> and this <hi>happineſs</hi> muſt be <hi>obtained</hi> by our <hi>prayers.</hi> Yea, I doubt not to aſſert, that our <hi>own advant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age is mainly neglected, when we neglect to pray for our Governours:</hi> and it is but <hi>juſt</hi> that God ſhould <hi>withdraw</hi> his <hi>bleſſings</hi> from us, when we <hi>forſake</hi> his <hi>preſcribed way</hi> for the <hi>keeping</hi> them. <hi>Hiſtories</hi> will ſufficiently acquaint us what good the very <hi>Heathen Emperors</hi> reaped by the <hi>prayers</hi> of their <hi>Chriſtian Souldiers,</hi> which tended many times to the <hi>furtherance of the Goſpel,</hi> by a greater <hi>indulgence</hi> to the profeſſors of it. Nay look at the <hi>Princes</hi> themſelves, and ſo you will ſee</p>
                  <p n="3">3. There is reaſon <hi>Ex parte ſui,</hi> with reſpect to <hi>Them;</hi> becauſe <hi>they ſtand in need of our prayers.</hi> Their <hi>Employment</hi> muſt needs be <hi>burdenſome,</hi> and a great many <hi>cares</hi> are put on with the <hi>Crown.</hi> All the <hi>concerns</hi> of the <hi>Common-Wealth</hi> are upon them as the <hi>head</hi> manageth the concerns of the <hi>body.</hi> There are <hi>variety of temptations</hi> to which their <hi>greatneſs</hi> renders them <hi>liable.</hi> Their pleaſures may encline them to <hi>voluptuouſneſs:</hi> and their power
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:37590:32"/>to <hi>tyranny:</hi> the rather becauſe <hi>unaccountable to their Subjects for what they do</hi> (however this <hi>doting age</hi> hath taught the <hi>contrary.</hi>) And then certainly there is a <hi>neceſſity</hi> we ſhould <hi>pray</hi> for them; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that God only hath the <hi>hearts</hi> of all men. particularly of <hi>Kings</hi> in his own <hi>hand:</hi> (<hi>The Kings heart is in the hand of the Lord, as the rivers of water, he turneth it whither ſo ever he will,</hi> Prov. 21.1.) that our <hi>ſupplications</hi> and <hi>interceſſions</hi> may <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail</hi> with him to <hi>encline</hi> thoſe <hi>hearts</hi> to <hi>good</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>evill.</hi> So much for the ſecond ſort, <hi>honor in ore, honour in the mouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The third is <hi>honor in opere: an honour</hi> mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in <hi>outward act.</hi> And this will beſt <hi>teſtifie the truth</hi> of that <hi>eſteem we bear in our hearts,</hi> and the <hi>ſincerity of thoſe prayers which proceed from our lips.</hi> Such an <hi>outward honour</hi> is due to <hi>Kings:</hi> and may be of two ſorts; 1 an <hi>honouring them with our Goods.</hi> 2 an <hi>honouring them with our Bodies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>An honouring them with our Goods.</hi> Thus <hi>Solomon</hi> uſeth the <hi>word. Honour the Lord with thy ſubſtance</hi> Prov. 3.9. It is a point of duty to <hi>pay</hi> what <hi>Kings impoſe.</hi> We know who reckoned <hi>this One</hi> of the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>The things which are Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars: Render unto Caeſar the things which are Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars,</hi> ſaith our <hi>Saviour</hi> Matt. 22.21. And the <hi>occaſion</hi> of thoſe words was a <hi>diſpute</hi> about <hi>tribute money.</hi> And thus the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> judged it. <hi>Tatianus</hi> (about 180 years after Chriſt) ſpeaks plainly <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In Orat. cont. Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos pag.</hi> 144. <hi>Edit. Morell.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Doth the King command me to pay tribute? I am ready to obey that command.</hi> I know it is a thing men will <hi>hardly</hi> be <hi>perſwaded</hi> unto, eſpecially when <hi>payments</hi> grow <hi>heavy,</hi> and <hi>purſes
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:37590:33"/>grow Light:</hi> when they have layen <hi>long,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue <hi>ſtill.</hi> But then conſider the <hi>engagement</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us from God, and that will ſerve to <hi>anſwer</hi> all <hi>objections.</hi> Our <hi>Saviour</hi> in that place, doth not ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>jus ſuum date, render</hi> him that which is <hi>his own:</hi> for a <hi>right</hi> to it he hath. Nay <hi>voluntariè date</hi> to <hi>render</hi> it him <hi>willingly</hi> and <hi>freely</hi> for this <hi>difference</hi> ſome <hi>Criticks</hi> make between <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the one takes in whatſoever the other includes, and adds to it a <hi>frankneſs</hi> and <hi>cheerfulneſs</hi> in the <hi>Giver.</hi> Our <hi>money</hi> hath the <hi>Kings ſtamp</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, and that <hi>vindicates</hi> his <hi>right</hi> to it. Two main <hi>motives</hi> there are which may <hi>encourage</hi> us in the paying <hi>this honour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Chriſts example</hi> in the very ſame caſe. <hi>He</hi> (ſaith <hi>St. Peter</hi> 1 Pet. 2.21.) <hi>hath left us an example that we ſhould follow his ſteps:</hi> and the Scripture hath <hi>remarked</hi> his <hi>example</hi> in the perf or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of <hi>this duty</hi> when in <hi>his Mothers Womb,</hi> a kind of <hi>Poll-money</hi> was laid by <hi>Auguſtus</hi> upon all his <hi>ſubjects,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 2 3, 4.</note> The bleſſed <hi>Virgin</hi> with her husband <hi>Joſeph, went to their own City to be taxed.</hi> Yea, the <hi>Divine Providence</hi> ſo <hi>ordered</hi> it, that <hi>while</hi> ſhe <hi>attended</hi> this <hi>payment,</hi> the <hi>Saviour of the world</hi> was <hi>born</hi> into the world. It cannot be denied but <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards</hi> he <hi>ſubmitted</hi> in this nature, when the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors</hi> came to St. <hi>Peter</hi> with that <hi>queſtion; Doth not your Maſter pay tribute?</hi> He anſwered yes, Matt. 17.24, 25. It ſeems he had <hi>formerly</hi> done it, and <hi>that</hi> was not the <hi>only time:</hi> though then he was willing to <hi>work a miracle</hi> rather than <hi>give offence</hi> by his <hi>backwardneſs <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Notwithſtanding</hi> leſt we ſhould offend them <hi>go thou to the Sea and caſt and book, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37590:33"/>take up the fiſh that firſt cometh up: and when thou haſt opened his mouth, thou ſhalt find a piece of money; that take, and give unto them for me and thee,</hi> verſe 27.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>Equity</hi> there is for it. Kings are <hi>Gods Miniſters,</hi> employed for the <hi>Common good,</hi> and therefore it is <hi>juſt</hi> they ſhould be <hi>well maintained</hi> by the <hi>common purſe. They</hi> are <hi>preſervers of peace, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viders for wars; neither</hi> of theſe can be <hi>done</hi> without <hi>contributions.</hi> They attend the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>ſervice</hi> of their <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, (it is the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> argument) for this cauſe pay you tribute alſo, <hi>for they are Gods Miniſters, attending continually upon this very thing,</hi> Rom. 13.6. But I preſume there is <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough</hi> (if not <hi>too much</hi>) ſaid upon this <hi>ſubject:</hi> Therefore</p>
                  <p n="2">2. There is an <hi>honouring them with our bodies:</hi> Whereby I mean <hi>a yielding obedience to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</hi> Thus the Apoſtle uſeth <hi>honour</hi> for <hi>obedience. Children obey your Parents:</hi> For which he cites the <hi>fifth Commandement, Honour thy Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> Epheſ. 6.1, 2. This is the ſame with St. Pauls <hi>ſubjection; Let every ſoul</hi> be ſubject <hi>to the higher powers,</hi> Rom. 13.1. and St. Peters <hi>ſubmiſſion;</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit <hi>your ſelves to every ordinance of man, for the Lords ſake,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13. What the <hi>Ancient Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> thought of <hi>this honour,</hi> we ſhall ſoon <hi>diſcern.</hi> Let <hi>one</hi> witneſs for <hi>all; Athenagoras,</hi> who flouriſhed about 150 Years after Chriſt.
<note place="margin">In Legat. pro Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anis ad Imp. Rom. ad finem.</note> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. We do willingly obey your Magiſtrates in all things which are commanded us.</hi> What thoſe all things are, we ſhall enquire <hi>preſently.</hi> In the mean while obſerve the <hi>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Your Governours,</hi>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:37590:34"/>ſpeaking to the Heathens: So that they concluded it a <hi>duty</hi> to <hi>live in ſubjection</hi> to the <hi>Emperours,</hi> though <hi>not owning the Chriſtian Faith.</hi> And me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, this <hi>ſpeech</hi> of his <hi>comments</hi> excellently up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that <hi>charge</hi> to <hi>Titus,</hi> as a <hi>diſpenſer</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel: put them in mind to be ſubject to Principalities and Powers, to obey Magiſtrates,</hi> Pit. 3.1. I know <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Princes</hi> is an unpleaſing doctrine, a <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel,</hi> which ſome mens <hi>throats</hi> are ſo <hi>narrow</hi> (not to meddle with their <hi>conſciences</hi>) they have much <hi>adoe</hi> to <hi>ſwallow:</hi> yet when all is <hi>alledged,</hi> it will appear their <hi>duty:</hi> whereto I could <hi>charitably</hi> hope, they might more eaſily be <hi>perſwaded,</hi> when once truly informed in its due <hi>latitude</hi> and <hi>extent.</hi> For the <hi>diſcovery</hi> whereof, let me lay down four <hi>Rules:</hi> having firſt <hi>premiſed</hi> in the general that <hi>obedience</hi> is of two ſorts; <hi>active,</hi> and <hi>paſſive:</hi> ſo that in <hi>ſome caſes</hi> the <hi>one,</hi> in <hi>ſome</hi> the <hi>other</hi> may <hi>concern</hi> us: Therefore</p>
                  <p>Rule 1. <hi>Where the commands of Princes</hi> are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, <hi>all Subjects are bound to an</hi> active <hi>obedience:</hi> which muſt be yielded <hi>heartily,</hi> and <hi>conſcienciouſly.</hi> Nay, I doubt not to aſſert that a <hi>paſſive obedience</hi> only in ſuch caſes <hi>renders</hi> us no better than <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſours. Magiſtrates</hi> ſhould find the <hi>people</hi> as <hi>ready</hi> to <hi>obey,</hi> as <hi>they</hi> are to <hi>enjoyn.</hi> And take notice I ſay, this <hi>obedience</hi> ſhould be yielded <hi>heartily</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcienciouſly:</hi> becauſe the <hi>command of God</hi> herein layes an <hi>obligation</hi> upon the <hi>conſcience. Ye muſt needs be ſubject, not onely for wrath, but alſo for</hi> conſcience ſake, Rom. 13.5. It is expreſsly a <hi>duty</hi> of the <hi>fifth commandement.</hi> They are our <hi>Civil Parents,</hi> and <hi>Children</hi> are bound to <hi>obey</hi> their <hi>Parents,</hi> though againſt their own <hi>inclinations,</hi> in things which be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:37590:34"/>
                     <hi>lawful.</hi> The onely <hi>difficulty</hi> will be wherein this <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> muſt be <hi>placed.</hi> For the underſtanding of which <hi>word,</hi> I affirm, that <hi>all things are lawful which are not ſinful:</hi> and <hi>ſin</hi> can onely be <hi>known</hi> by a <hi>violation</hi> of ſome <hi>Scripture-precept,</hi> either in <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect terms,</hi> or by <hi>neceſſary conſequence.</hi> This is the Apoſtles <hi>definition; ſin is a tranſgreſſion of the law,</hi> 1 John 3.4. If their <hi>injunctions</hi> prove <hi>in convenient,</hi> they are <hi>accountable to God</hi> for them; but that <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience</hi> doth not <hi>diſcharge</hi> us from our <hi>obedience.</hi> That this was the judgement of the <hi>firſt Chriſtians,</hi> I appeal to <hi>Ignatius,</hi> born before our Saviours <hi>crucifixion.
<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Antioch.</note> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Be obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to</hi> Caeſar, <hi>in thoſe things where your obedience may be without danger</hi> (and thoſe of <hi>that time</hi> valued no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as <hi>dangerous</hi> which was not <hi>ſinful.</hi>) Provoke not your Governours <hi>to wrath, that you give no occaſion to thoſe who ſeek occaſion againſt you.</hi> Now ſure this <hi>Holy Martyrs</hi> Teſtimony <hi>reacheth</hi> as far as my <hi>Rule,</hi> and further I perſwade no man: For</p>
                  <p>Rule 2. <hi>Where the commands of Princes are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, We are</hi> not <hi>to obey actively.</hi> It is <hi>poſſible</hi> there may be <hi>ſuch commands,</hi> and in <hi>ſuch caſes</hi> we muſt take up a reſolution of <hi>not obeying.</hi> The reaſon is becauſe we are <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>mainly</hi> obliged unto <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>no other obligation</hi> can lay a <hi>force</hi> upon us, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than it <hi>comports</hi> with that which we <hi>owe</hi> unto <hi>Him.</hi> It is therefore worth obſerving, that <hi>fear God, and honour the King</hi> are put <hi>together;</hi> as if the <hi>firſt</hi> were not onely a <hi>direction</hi> to, and an <hi>argument</hi> for, but a <hi>limitation</hi> alſo of the <hi>latter.</hi> Thus when
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:37590:35"/>the <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> were called by the <hi>Heathens</hi> to <hi>offer ſacrifice</hi> in their <hi>Temples,</hi> they gave this <hi>reply</hi> as <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> relates it:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In Apolog.</hi> 2. <hi>pro Chriſtianis pag.</hi> 64. <hi>Edit. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. We wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God alone, but in all things elſe we joyfully ſerve you.</hi> This was the caſe of the
<note n="*" place="margin">Dan. 3.17, 18.</note> 
                     <hi>three Children</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to <hi>adore</hi> Nebuchadnezzars <hi>golden Image,</hi> and <hi>refuſing;</hi> the caſe of
<note n="†" place="margin">Dan. 6.9, 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Daniel,</hi> when <hi>Darius</hi> decreed that no <hi>petition ſhould be made to God for ſo many dayes,</hi> and ſtill he <hi>continues</hi> in the courſe of his <hi>devotions:</hi> the caſe of the
<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 5.40, 42.</note> 
                     <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> when prohibited <hi>to preach Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> yet were they <hi>not afraid to ſpeak boldly in his name.</hi> But then we muſt remember thoſe things were <hi>ſimply unlawfull. Worſhipping Images</hi> a <hi>plain breach</hi> of the <hi>ſecond Commandement: neglect of prayer a ſin</hi> both againſt the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>ſecond:</hi> and the <hi>not preaching</hi> contrary to the very <hi>precept</hi> given to thoſe <hi>particular perſons: Ye ſhall be witneſſes unto me, both in</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and in all</hi> Judea, &amp;c. Acts 1.8. So then before we <hi>deny</hi> our <hi>active obedience,</hi> it is fit we be well <hi>ſatisfied</hi> the things are <hi>indeed unlawful,</hi> for which we deny it. <hi>Fancy</hi> or <hi>opinion</hi> will not <hi>ſerve</hi> the turn; Nay, a <hi>miſ-informed conſcience</hi> will not <hi>ſecure</hi> us from <hi>guilt:</hi> becauſe <hi>that miſ-information</hi> is in it <hi>ſelf</hi> a <hi>ſin.</hi> But if upon <hi>good ground</hi> we find they are <hi>ſuch,</hi> then</p>
                  <p>Rule 3. <hi>In caſe unlawful commands be laid upon us, we muſt</hi> quietly ſubmit <hi>to thoſe penalties which are appointed by the Laws of our Princes.</hi> And this is the true <hi>paſſive obedience.</hi> As <hi>ſin</hi> muſt not be <hi>committed,</hi> ſo <hi>ſuffering</hi> muſt not be <hi>declined.</hi> It is true, ſhall God afford a <hi>way of eſcape,</hi> ſo as <hi>liberty</hi> or <hi>life</hi> may be <hi>ſecured</hi> without <hi>violating our conſcience,</hi> we may <hi>thankefully accept</hi> it: but if <hi>not,</hi> we are <hi>engaged</hi> to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:37590:35"/>
                     <hi>ſubmit</hi> unto <hi>bonds, impriſonment,</hi> and <hi>death</hi> it ſelf, Thus the <hi>three Children</hi> though they would not <hi>worſhip</hi> the <hi>Image,
<note place="margin">Dan. 3.21.</note>
                        <note place="margin">Dan. 6.16.</note> refuſed not</hi> to be <hi>caſt into the fiery furnace:</hi> Thus <hi>Daniel,</hi> though after the <hi>decree,</hi> continuing his <hi>ſupplications; ſubmitted</hi> to be <hi>thrown into the Den of Lions:</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> though they <hi>deſiſted not</hi> from <hi>preaching,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 5.41. <hi>In Orat. cont. Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos pag.</hi> 144. <hi>Edit. Morell.</hi>
                     </note> yet took they their <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment patiently, rejoycing that they were counted worthy to ſuffer ſhame for his Name.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, was <hi>Tatianus</hi> his <hi>anſwer,</hi> when <hi>commanded</hi> to <hi>deny his God. It is the onely thing I ſhall refuſe to doe; but though I muſt not be perſwaded to it, I can be content to die for it.</hi> And <hi>Tertullian</hi> diſcourſing how the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> entertained thoſe <hi>ſevere ſentences</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt them;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In Apolog. cap.</hi> 50.</note> 
                     <hi>Sententiis veſtris gratias agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; cum damnamur à vobis, à Deo abſolvimur. We thank you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for them: becauſe when con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by you, we are abſolved by God.</hi> And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly this is the <hi>true way</hi> of <hi>learning</hi> our Saviours <hi>leſſon,</hi> Luke 21.19. <hi>In your patience poſſeſs ye your ſouls.</hi> Which will make way for the <hi>fourth Rule.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Rule 4. <hi>We are not upon the account of any unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful commands,</hi> to rebel againſt our King. God hath not <hi>in any caſe, allowed</hi> it: and it is directly <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> to that <hi>paſſive obedience</hi> which we are <hi>engaged</hi> to <hi>exerciſe. Solomon</hi> tells us of <hi>a King, againſt whom there is no riſing up,</hi> Prov. 30.31. <hi>For him</hi> we <hi>may,</hi> and <hi>ought</hi> to <hi>riſe; againſt him</hi> we <hi>may not. Wars, tumults, ſeditions,</hi> or the <hi>fomenting</hi> theſe, upon what <hi>pretence</hi> ſoever, by <hi>Subjects</hi> againſt their <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign,</hi> are <hi>utterly againſt the word of God.</hi> The <hi>peoples</hi> duty is <hi>ſubjection,</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> are <hi>accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37590:36"/>to God alone:</hi> it is not for us to <hi>uſurpe</hi> his <hi>place</hi> to <hi>correct</hi> or <hi>puniſh</hi> them at our <hi>pleaſure. My Son, fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change,</hi> Prov. 24.21. <hi>cum ſeditioſis,</hi> ſo ſome <hi>Tranſlations</hi> render it, with the <hi>ſeditious. Rebellion</hi> is a <hi>moſt grievous ſin,</hi> and it is <hi>impoſſible</hi> a <hi>Rebel</hi> ſhould ever be <hi>reconciled to God</hi> without <hi>a very great meaſure</hi> of <hi>repentance.</hi> The Apoſtle hath <hi>entailed damnation</hi> upon <hi>them: Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever reſiſteth the Powers, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God; and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves</hi> dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In Apolog. cap.</hi> 37.</note> Rom. 13.2. <hi>Tertullian applauding</hi> the <hi>qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſs</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> under their <hi>Heathen Governours,</hi> ſhewes plainly that if they <hi>durſt</hi> be <hi>Rebels,</hi> they might eaſily be <hi>Conquerors;</hi> or if <hi>not Conquerors,</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> would have ſo many <hi>fewer</hi> to <hi>defend him,</hi> they filling the <hi>Streets,</hi> and <hi>Cities,</hi> and <hi>Armies;</hi> and concluding againſt ſuch <hi>pernicious practices,</hi> tells how <hi>willingly</hi> they were <hi>ſlain,</hi> that they durſt not have a <hi>thought</hi> of <hi>rebelling;</hi> but on the contrary, <hi>nunc pauciores hoſtes habetis prae multitudine Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum. Now</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the number of our enemies is ſo much the leſs, by how much the number of Chriſtians is the greater.</hi> I have run through the <hi>doctrinal</hi> part of the <hi>Text,</hi> and ſhewed you wherein this <hi>Honour</hi> to the <hi>King conſiſts,</hi> and upon what <hi>grounds</hi> it is <hi>due:</hi> with ſome <hi>Rules</hi> to <hi>direct</hi> you in your <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> to their <hi>commands:</hi> Let me conclude all with a <hi>ſhort Application.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the <hi>uſe</hi> I inſiſt upon ſhall neither be a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof</hi> of <hi>former neglects,</hi>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                     </label>(men love not to have their <hi>ſore</hi> places <hi>rubbed</hi> too <hi>hard</hi>) nor of <hi>humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation</hi> for former <hi>errors,</hi> (God knows that is <hi>too proper</hi> for a 30 of <hi>January</hi>) but of <hi>exhortation</hi> to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:37590:36"/>
                     <hi>duty,</hi> and to <hi>the duty</hi> in the <hi>Text:</hi> If you be <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> you are <hi>obliged</hi> to <hi>this</hi> which is the <hi>duty</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> if the <hi>ſervants of</hi> God, you are <hi>bound</hi> to be <hi>ruled</hi> by the <hi>word of God.</hi> Yea let me ſay we have <hi>greater reaſon</hi> than <hi>thoſe</hi> who <hi>lived</hi> in the <hi>infancy of the Church. Their</hi> Princes were <hi>perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Heathens, ours</hi> is a <hi>Chriſtian King.</hi> Nay we have a <hi>ſtronger engagement</hi> upon us than to an <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Chriſtian King:</hi> if we <hi>reflect</hi> upon what God hath done <hi>for him</hi> and <hi>for us</hi> in him. And here let me but remind you of two things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. He is a <hi>King whom God wonderfully preſerved to bring unto his Throne: Covering</hi> him from the <hi>dangerous attempts</hi> of his <hi>enemies,</hi> under <hi>the ſhadow of his own wings.</hi> It is not fit we ſhould <hi>forget</hi> what <hi>ſnares</hi> were laid to <hi>entrap</hi> him before the <hi>barbarous murder</hi> of <hi>his Royall Father,</hi> what <hi>tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing offers</hi> were made to <hi>betray</hi> him after his <hi>eſcape</hi> from the <hi>defeat</hi> at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> How <hi>particular</hi> a <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> attended him in forreign <hi>Countries</hi> during his <hi>tedious exile.</hi> But with <hi>all imaginable thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> are we to <hi>commemorate</hi> the <hi>wonderfull good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God,</hi> who kept him <hi>unchangeable</hi> in his <hi>Religion</hi> amidſt the <hi>plauſible allurements</hi> of his <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh friends,</hi> and the <hi>deteſtable ingratitude</hi> of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Subjects. <hi>Large promiſes</hi> were made by the <hi>one</hi> in caſe he would <hi>countenance</hi> their <hi>Superſtitions:</hi> and the <hi>cunningeſt contrivances</hi> were laid by the <hi>other</hi> to <hi>ſupport</hi> their <hi>unjuſt intereſts.</hi> Yet God kept him <hi>untainted</hi> by the <hi>firſt,</hi> and rendred him <hi>ſecure</hi> from the <hi>latter: diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointing</hi> them in our own <hi>devices.</hi> For</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He is <hi>a King after ſuch preſervation, brought to his Kingdom by Gods miraculous power.</hi> It is true
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:37590:37"/>the <hi>hand of heaven</hi> may be ſeen in <hi>all things,</hi> but in <hi>ſome</hi> more <hi>viſibly</hi> than in <hi>others.</hi> I could <hi>almoſt</hi> ſay, <hi>few paſſages</hi> of <hi>Providence</hi> have been more <hi>ſtrangely remarkable</hi> than <hi>this</hi> whereof we ſpeak. To give you a ſhort account of it. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the <hi>variety of intereſts</hi> abroad in the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> notwithſtanding the <hi>multitude</hi> of <hi>foes</hi> we may eaſily imagine he <hi>had, ſome</hi> drawn to be ſo for <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>loſing their eſtates, ſome</hi> of <hi>their lives:</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the <hi>ſeveral attempts</hi> for his <hi>reſtauration</hi> which had proved <hi>fruitleſs,</hi> and the <hi>various projects</hi> which had been <hi>diſ-appointed;</hi> yet <hi>God</hi> wrought his <hi>own work</hi> in his <hi>own way,</hi> at <hi>his own time.</hi> He ſtirred up a <hi>Noble-Hearted Subject</hi> our <hi>renowned Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall,</hi> (whom God <hi>long bleſs,</hi> for bringing ſuch a <hi>bleſſing</hi> to us) directed him in the <hi>management</hi> of his <hi>affairs,</hi> made him <hi>ſucceſsfull</hi> in his <hi>enterprizes,</hi> by whoſe <hi>wiſdom, courage,</hi> and <hi>faithfulneſs,</hi> our <hi>King</hi> was <hi>brought home quietly,</hi> and <hi>peaceably,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>ſhedding one drop</hi> of <hi>blood.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Kings 6.7.</note> I was going to ſay, his <hi>return</hi> was like the <hi>building</hi> of <hi>Solomons Temple, without noiſe;</hi> but that the <hi>Solemnities</hi> of <hi>this day</hi> proved it <hi>otherwiſe:</hi> when the <hi>Canons</hi> in the <hi>Tower,</hi> the <hi>Bells</hi> in the <hi>Churches,</hi> and the <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations</hi> of the <hi>people vied</hi> one with another, which ſhould <hi>loudlieſt proclaim</hi> his <hi>welcome to Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> Certainly, God did herein <hi>out-do</hi> our very <hi>expectations.</hi> It is <hi>a day</hi> we have reaſon to <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> it brought us a <hi>mercy</hi> we have reaſon to <hi>prize.</hi> To ſum up all, Let us be ſure to <hi>honour</hi> that <hi>King,</hi> whom God by ſuch a <hi>miraculous preſervation</hi> hath <hi>honoured.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 118.24.</note> And ſince <hi>this is the day which the Lord hath made, we will rejoice and be glad in it: bleſſing</hi> and <hi>praiſing</hi> the <hi>great worker of wonders</hi> for
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:37590:37"/>this his <hi>wonderfull mercy</hi> vouchſafed unto us. For <hi>which,</hi> and all other <hi>benefits</hi> beſtowed upon us, To the <hi>Eternall,</hi> and <hi>Glorious Trinity, Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> be continually aſcribed <hi>Glory, Praiſe, Dominion,</hi> and <hi>Thanksgiving,</hi> now henceforth, and for evermore. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:37590:38"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:37590:38"/>
                  <p>Davids WORK AND REST. A SERMON Preached at St. <hi>Martins</hi> Church, in <hi>Leiceſter, September</hi> 21. 1669. Before the Election of the Mayor.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Tho. Stanhope A. M.</hi> Vicar of St. <hi>Margarets</hi> in <hi>Leiceſter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:37590:39"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:37590:39"/>
                  <head>TO THE Right VVorshipful The Mayor and Aldermen of the Borough of <hi>Leiceſter.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Right Worſhipful,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Here preſent to your Eyes what formerly was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to your Ears, God grant it may make a deep impreſſion upon your Hearts. It is a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preached by Command, and was at the preaching, favourably enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the perſons principally
<pb facs="tcp:37590:40"/>concerned in it. To prevent the trouble of giving ſeveral Copies deſired by ſome good Friends, (which <hi>I</hi> thought might be attended with ſundry Inconveniencies) I have choſen this way of publiſhing it in Print, that it may be ready at hand to do God, his Church, and your ſelves a further ſervice. I muſt ever thankfully remember the kindneſs received by an unanimous vote in your Hall, at my firſt ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment among you; and the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of a fair Reſpect, which as I ſtill experience, ſo I deſire to declare it to the World. My capacity will not reach to a better acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than the offering this Token of Gratitude into your hands. God
<pb facs="tcp:37590:40"/>Almighty bleſs it to the good end for which it was deſigned; that by fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Davids example in <hi>ſerving your Generations,</hi> His Holy Name may receive due Honour, you may be Inſtrumental to do much good, and your Corporation (being Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned with Care and Conſcience) may flouriſh in Peace, and Plenty, while the Sun and Moon endure. This is and ſhall be the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Prayer of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Humble Servant in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Tho. Stanhope.</signed> 
                     <dateline>Leiceſter <date>Novem. <hi>9. 1669.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:37590:41"/>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:37590:41"/>
                  <head>DAVIDS Work and Reſt.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Acts 13.36.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>For <hi>David</hi> after he had ſerved his own Generation by the Will of God, fell on ſleep.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is no <hi>new thing</hi> in Scripture to meet with <hi>Articles of Faith</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by <hi>force of Argument. Rational proofes</hi> make the <hi>deepeſt impreſſion</hi> upon <hi>rational creatures.</hi> Thus <hi>St. Paul</hi> ſpends a <hi>whole Chapter</hi> in proving the <hi>Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>our</hi> bodies, 1 Cor 15. And here <hi>great part</hi> of a <hi>Sermon</hi> in proving the <hi>reſurrection</hi> of <hi>Chriſts</hi> body. The <hi>medium</hi> he uſeth is a paſſage of <hi>Davids,</hi> which
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:37590:42"/>that <hi>Prophetick Pſalmiſt</hi> had long before ſung, in <hi>his name,</hi> upon a <hi>foreſight</hi> of his <hi>triumph</hi> over <hi>death,</hi> Pſal. 16.10. <hi>Thou wilt not leave my ſoul in bell, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wilt thou ſuffer thine Holy One to ſee corruption.</hi> Now that theſe <hi>words</hi> were a <hi>praediction</hi> concerning <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Apoſtle makes out <hi>Syllogiſtically:</hi> one <hi>part</hi> of the <hi>Argument</hi> being <hi>implied,</hi> the other part <hi>expreſſed.</hi> That <hi>implied</hi> is the <hi>ground</hi> or <hi>foundation</hi> of the reſt, and may thus be formed. <hi>Either this place muſt be underſtood of</hi> David, <hi>or of Chriſt: But it cannot be underſtood of</hi> David: Therefore <hi>it muſt be underſtood of</hi> Chriſt. Where the <hi>Minor</hi> being on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lyable to <hi>exception,</hi> is <hi>ſtrengthened</hi> by that which we find expreſſed. The <hi>two propoſitions</hi> are in <hi>two verſes.</hi> David <hi>after he had ſerved his own generation by the Will of God, fell on ſleep, and ſaw corruption,</hi> in <hi>this; But</hi> he <hi>whom God raiſed up</hi> (meaning Chriſt) <hi>ſaw no corruption,</hi> in the <hi>next.</hi> Whence the <hi>conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> naturally follows; <hi>Therefore</hi> the Pſalmiſts words of <hi>not ſeeing corruption</hi> muſt be <hi>underſtood not</hi> of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> but of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And thus the Text ſtands in its <hi>relative conſideration:</hi> as it reſpects the <hi>buſineſs</hi> our Apoſtle was then <hi>managing,</hi> and the <hi>Article of faith</hi> he was then <hi>confirming.</hi> But I paſs from <hi>that,</hi> to take it <hi>abſolutely;</hi> as it neither looks <hi>backward</hi> nor <hi>forward,</hi> yet contains in it <hi>ſelf</hi> thoſe <hi>truths</hi> which may be <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> for this <hi>occaſion,</hi> for this <hi>Auditory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For</hi> David, <hi>after he had ſerved,</hi> &amp;c. To enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain you with any <hi>tedious diſcourſe</hi> of <hi>Davids perſon,</hi> or <hi>Criticiſones</hi> upon his <hi>Name,</hi> would be ill husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry both of your <hi>patience</hi> and my <hi>time.</hi> His <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> is ſo exactly <hi>given</hi> by the <hi>Spirit of truth,</hi> and his <hi>life</hi> ſo largely <hi>written</hi> in the <hi>Scriptures of truth,</hi> that he who <hi>runs</hi> may <hi>read,</hi> and he
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:37590:42"/>who reads may <hi>underſtand</hi> them. I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine my ſelf to what is here mentioned. <hi>After he had</hi> ſerved <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; the Subſtantive whence the <hi>Verb</hi> comes properly ſignifies an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder-rewer, ab</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ſub remige, qui remum in navi agit;</hi> he that <hi>tugs</hi> at the <hi>oare</hi> in the <hi>Ship;</hi> a Work of <hi>conſtant</hi> and <hi>extraordinary pains.</hi> And it is <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly</hi> (if not <hi>alwayes</hi> in the New Teſtament) uſed of <hi>ſerving in Publick Employments:</hi> a ſign that men when <hi>called</hi> to the <hi>Management</hi> of <hi>great Offices,</hi> are <hi>called</hi> to a <hi>great deal</hi> of <hi>trouble.</hi> The <hi>Mace</hi> and the <hi>Scarlet</hi> doe not more <hi>naturally</hi> bring <hi>bonour</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect,</hi> than <hi>care</hi> and <hi>toile</hi> along with them. No mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel then that <hi>honos</hi> and <hi>onus</hi> ſound ſo <hi>like,</hi> or the Hebrew <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> tranſlated <hi>honour</hi> ſhould be derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> which ſignifies to <hi>be burdenſome.</hi> Men will ſcarce believe that <hi>King</hi> ſpake his <hi>thoughts,</hi> when he told the <hi>Woman</hi> applauding his <hi>happineſs: Kneweſt thou what cares are wrapt up in a Crown,</hi> ne ex luto quidem, <hi>thou wouldſt not take it up out of the dirt:</hi> but he that <hi>wore</hi> it, <hi>felt</hi> how <hi>heavy</hi> it <hi>ſat</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and made both his <hi>head</hi> and <hi>ſhoulders</hi> to <hi>ake.</hi> That by the way. <hi>After he had ſerved his own Generation</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, To underſtand this <hi>word</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, you muſt know that <hi>Generation</hi> is eſpecially taken <hi>two</hi> wayes: either for <hi>the whole time one lives,</hi> the <hi>duration of a particular mans life,</hi> as Deut. 1.35. <hi>Surely there ſhall none of the men of this evill Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſee that good Land,</hi> i.e. <hi>none</hi> of the <hi>Iſraelites at that time living and grown up.</hi> For the beſt <hi>Comment</hi> upon that Text is, the <hi>Execution</hi> of the <hi>Judgement</hi> according to the <hi>threatning:</hi> And we know that <hi>execution</hi> was <hi>general,</hi> none <hi>eſcaping</hi> but thoſe <hi>two excepted</hi> by God himſelf, <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſhua.</hi> And
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:37590:43"/>ſo our <hi>learned</hi> Doctor <hi>Hammond</hi> explains theſe Words;
<note place="margin">Paraph. on the Text.</note> David <hi>having lived his ſpace, or term of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural life:</hi> Or elſe it is taken for <hi>the people living to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in ſome one Age,</hi> as Heb. 3.10. <hi>Wherefore I was grieved with that Generation,</hi> i. e. with <hi>the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elitiſh people living in that Age:</hi> And thus we may underſtand the words of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Eccleſ. 1.4. <hi>One</hi> Generation paſſeth away, and another Generation <hi>cometh,</hi> i.e. <hi>one body of men who have lived together, die, and another riſeth up in their ſtead.</hi> And if we cloſe with <hi>this ſence</hi> (as very <hi>well</hi> we may doe, <hi>take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in the <hi>other</hi> alſo) then the Text refers to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> as a <hi>publick perſon,</hi> and thus far it may be <hi>para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſed</hi> on this manner. David, <hi>having</hi> whilſt his term of life endured, <hi>diſcharged the duties incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent upon him</hi> towards the people of his time, <hi>as a King or Magiſtrate. By the will of God.</hi> The omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Praepoſitions</hi> in this place hath made it <hi>capable</hi> of <hi>two different readings.</hi> Either with <hi>ſome,</hi> David <hi>in his own Generation having ſerved the counſel of God</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) or with <hi>us,</hi> David <hi>after he bad ſerved his own Generation, by the will of God.</hi> And ſay this were <hi>none,</hi> there is <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther difficulty</hi> remaining, whether the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhould be <hi>joynd</hi> with the <hi>praecedent</hi> or <hi>ſubſequent</hi> words. The <hi>will of God</hi> is ordinarily <hi>diſtinguiſhed</hi> into his <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas occulta,</hi> and his <hi>volunt as revelata:</hi> his <hi>ſecret,</hi> and his <hi>revealed will:</hi> if you underſtand this place of the <hi>firſt,</hi> then it will fitlieſt <hi>joyn</hi> with <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, thus: David <hi>having whilſt he lived, carefully diſcharged his Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratical office:</hi> according to the Decree of God he fell aſleep. If you underſtand it of the <hi>ſecond,</hi> then it will beſt be <hi>annexed</hi> to the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, thus: David <hi>having on this manner diſcharged
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:37590:43"/>his duty,</hi> according to the will of God revealed unto him, <hi>he fell on ſleep,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. It is ordinary to find <hi>death</hi> in Scripture expreſſed by <hi>ſleep, for this cauſe, many are weak, and ſickly, and many</hi> ſleep, 1 Cor. 11.30. And our <hi>Church-yards</hi> the <hi>uſual bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-places</hi> are called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ſleeping-roomes.</hi> The <hi>reaſon</hi> of it (in ſhort) ſeems to be this, that as our <hi>ſleeps</hi> are but for a <hi>night,</hi> from which we <hi>awake</hi> in the <hi>morning;</hi> ſo the <hi>reſting</hi> of our <hi>bodies</hi> in the <hi>grave,</hi> is but till the <hi>morning</hi> of the great <hi>reſurrection day; when the trumpet ſhall ſound,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.52.</note> and the dead ſhall be raiſed <hi>and we ſhall be changed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The words thus <hi>explained,</hi> do naturally <hi>divide</hi> themſelves into <hi>two</hi> parts: 1. Here is <hi>Davids work; after he had ſerved his own Generation, by the will of God;</hi> 2. Here is <hi>Davids reſt; he fell on ſleep.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Here is <hi>Davids work: He ſerved his own Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration by the will of God.</hi> It is but <hi>reaſonable</hi> to <hi>believe,</hi> God <hi>knows</hi> beſt where to <hi>chuſe</hi> thoſe may do him the moſt <hi>ſervice.</hi> He that <hi>employs</hi> men can <hi>tell</hi> who are <hi>fitteſt</hi> to be <hi>employed:</hi> ſo that <hi>himſelf</hi> pitching upon <hi>David,</hi> at the rejection of <hi>Saul,</hi> and having ſaid, <hi>I have found David</hi> my ſervant, <hi>with my holy oyl have I anointed him, with whom my hand ſhall be eſtabliſhed, mine Arm alſo ſhall ſtrengthen him.</hi> Pſal. 89.20, 21. No marvell if he <hi>fulfilled all his will:</hi> if he <hi>fed his people accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the integrity of his heart,
<note place="margin">Acts 13.22. Pſal. 78.72.</note> and guided them by the skilfulneſs of his hand.</hi> For though he be an <hi>excellent pattern</hi> in his <hi>perſonal,</hi> yet he is <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally remarkeable</hi> in his <hi>politick capacity. Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> queſtionleſs he had in <hi>both,</hi> and ſo will <hi>all Kings</hi> and <hi>Governours,</hi> while they carry <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> about with them; but thoſe <hi>eminent qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations</hi>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:37590:44"/>wherewith he was <hi>endowed,</hi> thoſe <hi>admirable vertues</hi> which <hi>ſhined</hi> in his <hi>ſoul,</hi> the <hi>conſtant man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement</hi> of <hi>publick affairs,</hi> with <hi>piety</hi> and <hi>juſtice</hi> (however <hi>wanting</hi> in ſome <hi>particular acts</hi>) have <hi>gained</hi> him this <hi>Encomium</hi> from the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> that <hi>he ſerved his own Generation by the will of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>work</hi> wherein we are <hi>now employed</hi> was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly deſigned as a <hi>preparative</hi> to that which <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,</hi> and wherein <hi>you</hi> are <hi>moſt concerned.</hi> And I doubt not but the <hi>text</hi> will <hi>anſwer</hi> that <hi>deſign.</hi> We are now conſidering <hi>David as a Magiſtrate,</hi> and how as a <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> he <hi>ſerved his Generation:</hi> The <hi>iſſue</hi> whereof (I hope) will be the ſhewing <hi>you</hi> that are <hi>Magiſtrates already,</hi> your <hi>duty;</hi> and the <hi>informing</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who ſhall <hi>ſucceed</hi> you; what <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>people</hi> expect at their <hi>bands.</hi> It is needleſs to ſpend time in <hi>generals,</hi> and therefore I paſs to <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>David ſerved his own Generation,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>by his zeal for the worſhip of God.</hi> The <hi>main object</hi> of his <hi>pious care</hi> was the <hi>furtherance</hi> and <hi>flouriſhing ſettlement</hi> of Gods <hi>ſervice.</hi> The <hi>Ark</hi> that <hi>token</hi> of the <hi>Divine preſence,</hi> had been taken by the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines</hi> at the fatall battel, wherein <hi>Elies</hi> Sons were ſlain; and though they were forced to ſend <hi>it</hi> out of their borders, by reaſon of the Plagues among them, yet it remained in an <hi>obſcure place.</hi> But no ſooner was <hi>David ſettled</hi> in his <hi>Kingdom</hi> than he takes order for <hi>its conduct</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and <hi>ſets it in its place in the midſt of the Tabernacle he had pitched for it,</hi> 2 Sam. 6.17. Nor would that <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent</hi> him,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 7.2, 3. &amp;c.</note> Loth he was while <hi>himſelf dwelt in an houſe of Cedar, that the Ark of God ſhould dwell within Curtains:</hi> and therefore he <hi>purpoſeth to build a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:37590:44"/>Temple:</hi> which though not <hi>permitted</hi> to <hi>raiſe,</hi> yet he <hi>provides materials</hi> to a <hi>vaſt quantity:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Chron. 24.25. &amp;c.</note> and <hi>ſets the Prieſts in their courſes, appointing them their ſolemn ſervices.</hi> And indeed, if the <hi>Magiſtrate help not</hi> in <hi>this</hi> great <hi>work</hi> who <hi>ſhould? He</hi> by his <hi>office</hi> is <hi>cuſtos utriuſque tabulae, both tables</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> are <hi>committed</hi> to <hi>him,</hi> and he muſt be <hi>zealous</hi> for the <hi>due obſervance</hi> of <hi>both.</hi> Doth he <hi>deſerve</hi> the <hi>Name</hi> of a God, who <hi>neglects</hi> the <hi>concerns</hi> of that <hi>God</hi> whoſe <hi>name he bears?</hi> Look through the <hi>ſtories</hi> of the <hi>Kings,</hi> and you ſhall ſtill find the <hi>beſt</hi> of them moſt <hi>ſollicitous</hi> in this <hi>point.</hi> Witneſs thoſe <hi>ſolemn Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>overs</hi> in the times of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Joſiah, the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down the brazen ſerpent,</hi> the <hi>idolatrous temples and groves, taking away the Prieſts of Baal,</hi> and the <hi>high places,</hi> effected by thoſe <hi>two pious Princes.</hi> I wiſh all in <hi>Authority</hi> would <hi>imitate</hi> ſuch excellent <hi>examples. It is good to be zealouſly affected always</hi> in a good thing, ſaith the Apoſtle, Galat. 4.18. And I am ſure the <hi>worſhip of God</hi> may <hi>challenge</hi> that <hi>term</hi> upon the <hi>greateſt</hi> reaſon. <hi>Good,</hi> as an <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable homage</hi> to our <hi>good</hi> God; and <hi>good,</hi> as the <hi>ready way</hi> to procure <hi>good</hi> to our <hi>immortall ſouls.</hi> This then I deſire to <hi>charge</hi> upon <hi>all</hi> in <hi>publick offices.</hi> Let thoſe that are about you diſcern your <hi>vigour</hi> and <hi>activity</hi> for His <hi>ſervice</hi> by <hi>whom</hi> you are <hi>advanced. Spare</hi> no <hi>pains</hi> in <hi>furthering</hi> it, <hi>neglect</hi> no <hi>means conducing</hi> to it. And remember that when you <hi>act</hi> for <hi>him</hi> you <hi>act</hi> for <hi>your ſelves,</hi> when you <hi>endeavour</hi> his <hi>glory</hi> he will be ſure to <hi>enhaunce yours:</hi> according to his <hi>promiſe,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.30. <hi>Them that honour me, I will</hi> honour; <hi>but they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly eſteemed.</hi> But <hi>Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> is a word of <hi>large extent,</hi> and <hi>camprehends</hi>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:37590:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>many <hi>things</hi> under it: I humbly crave leave to be your <hi>remembrancer</hi> of theſe <hi>two.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Let no</hi> falſe worſhip <hi>be countenanced within your Juriſdiction.</hi> Let not <hi>Dagon</hi> be ſet ſo <hi>near</hi> the <hi>Ark,</hi> nor an <hi>Altar</hi> for <hi>Baal</hi> be <hi>reared</hi> by the <hi>Altar</hi> of the <hi>God of Iſrael. Zeal</hi> (againſt the <hi>rules</hi> of <hi>Grammar</hi>) begins <hi>to decline</hi> at the <hi>ablative,</hi> as well knowing that a <hi>true worſhip</hi> can never be <hi>advanced,</hi> till <hi>all falſe worſhips</hi> be <hi>ſuppreſſed.</hi> Whilſt like the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Kings 17.41.</note> we <hi>fear the Lord,</hi> and <hi>worſhip</hi> our <hi>graven Images;</hi> we are <hi>party-per-pale,</hi> Chriſtians and <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> work of <hi>good Hezekiah</hi> was to <hi>throw down</hi> the <hi>high places,</hi> and to make <hi>the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen Serpent Nehuſhtan,</hi> 2 Kings 18.4. If any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire whither this <hi>advice tends,</hi> my <hi>anſwer</hi> briefly ſhall be,
<note place="margin">Luke 23.33.</note> Every <hi>Conſiderative man</hi> may eaſily <hi>diſcern</hi> that the <hi>Church of England</hi> like <hi>Chriſt</hi> its <hi>husband</hi> is <hi>crucified between two malefactors:</hi> The <hi>Papiſt</hi> on the <hi>one hand,</hi> and the <hi>Separatiſt</hi> on the <hi>other: both</hi> theſe would have <hi>their worſhip</hi> in <hi>contempt</hi> of and <hi>oppoſition</hi> to <hi>ours:</hi> which brings an <hi>Odium</hi> upon our <hi>Religion.</hi> And certainly if <hi>thoſe</hi> who have <hi>power</hi> in their <hi>hands improve</hi> not their <hi>power</hi> to <hi>vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> that <hi>Church</hi> whereof they are <hi>members,</hi> their <hi>account</hi> will be <hi>heavy,</hi> when the <hi>greateſt</hi> muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before <hi>one greater</hi> than they: and receive a <hi>reward</hi> according to the <hi>diſcharge</hi> of their <hi>places.</hi> No matter how <hi>fooliſh people ſpend</hi> their <hi>Lungs,</hi> and <hi>ſtrain</hi> their <hi>throats</hi> to <hi>cry</hi> up <hi>liberty of conſcience.</hi> It is a thing which <hi>once admitted</hi> would make our <hi>England</hi> an <hi>Amſterdam.</hi> And if <hi>arguments</hi> will not <hi>convince</hi> us, <hi>ſad experience may,</hi> that nothing is more <hi>intolſerable</hi> than a <hi>toleration of opinions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Take care that the Lords-day be kept holy.</hi> That
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:37590:45"/>God may be <hi>worſhipped</hi> it is neceſſary ſome <hi>time</hi> be ſet <hi>apart</hi> for his <hi>worſhip;</hi> and what time <hi>fitter</hi> than that which is already <hi>appointed?</hi> wherein then can <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> more <hi>promote Gods worſhip</hi> than by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding that <hi>this day</hi> be <hi>ſpent</hi> in it? How vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly did <hi>Nehemiah</hi> appear in <hi>ſanctifying</hi> the <hi>legall Sabbath, chiding with the Nobles of Judah, ſhutting the Gates in the evening, before the day declined, and not opening them till the Sabbath was ended,</hi> nay, <hi>ſetting his own ſervants to watch the gates,</hi> and <hi>not ſuffering the Merchants) and Tradeſmen to lodge within the City</hi> Nehem. 13.17, 19, 20. I argue not for a <hi>Jewiſh Sabbath,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Omnes dies do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicos cum omni venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vimus ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervart, et a ſervili o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neri, et ut mercatus in eis mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimè ſit, nec placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ubi a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquis ad mortem vel ad poenam judicetur Concil. Mogunt. can</hi> 37. <hi>Vid. Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chuin in</hi> 4 <hi>Precept.</hi> Exod 20.8.</note> but a <hi>Chriſtian Lords<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day;</hi> which had we <hi>nothing elſe,</hi> the argument <hi>à for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiori</hi> would <hi>engage</hi> us unto, If <hi>they</hi> under the <hi>law</hi> muſt ſet apart <hi>one</hi> day: in <hi>ſeven</hi> to <hi>remember</hi> the <hi>great work</hi> of <hi>Creation;</hi> well may <hi>we</hi> under the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to <hi>commemorate</hi> our <hi>redemption,</hi> without which <hi>creation</hi> had done us <hi>no good.</hi> And truly I am ſorry there is ſo much <hi>reaſon</hi> for this <hi>advice.</hi> Men generally, <hi>forbear bodily labour,</hi> and <hi>ſuffer</hi> themſelves to be <hi>worſe employed:</hi> giving the <hi>leaſt part</hi> of that <hi>day</hi> to <hi>him,</hi> whoſe <hi>due</hi> the <hi>whole</hi> of <hi>it</hi> is. It is a <hi>ſhame</hi> that an <hi>uſurped power</hi> ſhould bring people into <hi>better order</hi> than all the <hi>commands</hi> of <hi>lawfull Authority.</hi> It is not <hi>many years</hi> ſince a <hi>ſtrict Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation</hi> came forth for keeping <hi>this day Holy,</hi> and <hi>frequenting</hi> Church both <hi>evening</hi> and <hi>morning.</hi> I hope <hi>you</hi> will ſee that ſo <hi>Religious</hi> a <hi>Command</hi> be <hi>obſerved.</hi> And forget not that the <hi>fourth Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> is directly <hi>charged</hi> upon the <hi>head</hi> of a <hi>Family</hi> (and by the ſame reaſon <hi>reacheth</hi>) the <hi>head</hi> of a <hi>Corporation. Remember that thou keep holy the Sabbath day:</hi> as if the <hi>duty</hi> were <hi>only
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:37590:46"/>his,</hi> or the <hi>omiſſion</hi> of <hi>inferiours</hi> ſhould be <hi>ſet</hi> upon the <hi>ſuperiours ſcore.</hi> It is (through Gods bleſſing) in your hand to <hi>rectifie</hi> all <hi>abuſes</hi> of this <hi>nature:</hi> your <hi>Authority</hi> will <hi>force</hi> men to <hi>Church, keep</hi> them both out of <hi>Ale-houſes</hi> and <hi>Idleneſs,</hi> when our <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons cannot.</hi> And therefore we humbly <hi>beg</hi> your <hi>help,</hi> that God be not <hi>provoked</hi> to <hi>curſe</hi> the <hi>work</hi> of our days becauſe we <hi>deſpiſe</hi> the <hi>work</hi> of <hi>his:</hi> and <hi>blaſt</hi> all our <hi>diligence</hi> on the <hi>ſix,</hi> for our <hi>prophanation</hi> of the <hi>ſeventh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>David</hi> ſerved his <hi>Generation</hi> and <hi>by puniſhing contumacious offenders. I will early deſtroy all the wicked of the Land, that I may cut off all wicked do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers from the City of the Lord</hi> Pſal. 101.8. When the <hi>Amalekite</hi> came with the news that he had <hi>ſlain Saul, David ſlew</hi> him: 2 Sam. 1.15. When <hi>Baanah</hi> and <hi>Rechab</hi> had <hi>killed Iſhboſheth,</hi> he <hi>killed</hi> them: 2 Sam. 4.12. yet the <hi>one</hi> was his <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> his <hi>competitor</hi> for the <hi>Kingdom.</hi> Afterwards, when <hi>Joab</hi> had <hi>ſinitten Abner</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſa;</hi> (of whom (I mean <hi>Joab</hi>) it might be ſaid as once of <hi>Origen, ubi benè nemo melius, ubi malè nemo pejus: Where he did well no man did better; and where he did ill no man did worſe</hi>) and when <hi>Shimei</hi> had <hi>curſed David,</hi> though his <hi>Reign</hi> was ſo <hi>troubleſome</hi> that he could not take <hi>vengeance</hi> on <hi>them</hi> in his <hi>life;</hi> yet he leaves it in <hi>charge</hi> to <hi>Solomon</hi> 1 Kings 2.5, 6, 8, 9. <hi>Puniſhments</hi> of ſuch <hi>high nature</hi> poſſibly <hi>fall</hi> not within <hi>your compaſs;</hi> yet herein it is fit you <hi>imitate David,</hi> and hereby alſo you ſhall <hi>ſerve your Generation,</hi> in not <hi>ſuffering</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>guilty perſons</hi> which come before you to <hi>glory</hi> in <hi>impunity. Pity</hi> and <hi>lenity</hi> do well <hi>become</hi> a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate</hi> where they may do <hi>good;</hi> but if the <hi>ſore</hi>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:37590:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>will onely <hi>rankle</hi> with <hi>plaiſters,</hi> it is time to apply <hi>tents</hi> and <hi>corroſives.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Comerari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us apud Godwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num de Antiquit. Roman. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Bonum eſt cum puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes. Quis hoe niſi nocens negabit? Tertul. de ſpectaculis cap</hi>
                     </note> The <hi>Conſuls</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> had both <hi>rods</hi> and <hi>axes</hi> carried <hi>before</hi> them: <hi>Rods,</hi> as <hi>enſigns of mercy,</hi> if the <hi>offences</hi> were <hi>leſs,</hi> and the <hi>offenders penitent, axes,</hi> as <hi>tokens of ſeverity,</hi> if the <hi>offences</hi> were <hi>greater,</hi> and the <hi>offenders incorrigible.</hi> You know <hi>who</hi> hath ſaid, <hi>To acquit the wicked, and to condemn the righteous, both of them are abomination to the Lord,</hi> Prov. 17.15. Nay, let me tell you that a <hi>ſparing</hi> thoſe who are <hi>evil,</hi> is a <hi>diſcouragement,</hi> a <hi>wrong</hi> to thoſe that are <hi>good. Magiſtratus qui de ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis paenas nòn ſumit, bonos injuriâ afficit,</hi> ſaid old <hi>Pythagoras; That Magiſtrate who corrects not the faulty, injures the blameleſs.</hi> I adde further, it <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feoffes</hi> you in the <hi>ſame guilt</hi> with them. It is a known <hi>ſtory</hi> how <hi>tart,</hi> yet how <hi>true</hi> an <hi>anſwer</hi> was made to the <hi>Judge,</hi> who <hi>expoſtulating</hi> with a <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor,</hi> and <hi>pleading</hi> for how <hi>many crimes</hi> he had been <hi>pardoned,</hi> was told, that <hi>thoſe crimes were not the mans, but his,</hi> becauſe he had <hi>forgiven</hi> him, and <hi>not puniſhed</hi> him according to his <hi>deſerts.</hi> And the <hi>beſt</hi> of us have <hi>ſins enough</hi> of our <hi>own,</hi> that we need not <hi>graſp</hi> at thoſe of <hi>others.</hi> The truth is, God hath directly <hi>pointed</hi> you to this duty in the <hi>Name</hi> he hath given you, Rom. 13.4.
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>He beareth not the ſword in vain, for he is the Miniſter of God, a reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to execute wrath upon him that doth evil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. David <hi>ſerved his Generation; and by his courage and reſolution in the wayes of God,</hi> All the <hi>difficulties</hi> which <hi>attended</hi> him, all the <hi>affronts</hi> he <hi>met</hi> with, all the <hi>afflictions</hi> through which he <hi>waded,</hi> could not <hi>damp</hi> his <hi>reſolute ſpirit</hi> from <hi>retaining his integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> or <hi>draw</hi> him from his <hi>God.</hi> Michal <hi>ſcoffs</hi> when he <hi>danceth before the Arke,</hi> and he tells her, <hi>I will
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:37590:47"/>yet be more vile than thus, and will be baſe in mine own ſight,</hi> 2 Sam. 6.22. The <hi>Grandees</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> thereabouts, <hi>ſat and ſpake againſt him, yet did he meditate in Gods ſtatutes,</hi> Pſal. 119.23. Nay, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he <hi>endured</hi> ſome <hi>cauſeleſs perſecutions,</hi> yet <hi>his heart ſtood in awe of Gods word</hi> verſe 161. He could not be <hi>daunted</hi> with the <hi>face</hi> of the <hi>greateſt: I will ſpeak of thy teſtimonies before Kings, and will not be aſhamed</hi> verſe 46. A <hi>Lyons heart</hi> is not more <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite</hi> in a <hi>Chyrurgion</hi> than in a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> that he <hi>firmly</hi> and <hi>ſtedfaſtly purpoſe</hi> with himſelf, not to be <hi>diſcoueaged</hi> at whatſoever <hi>happens;</hi> that nothing <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie</hi> or <hi>affright</hi> him; that neither <hi>threats</hi> nor <hi>frowns,</hi> neither <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>wnings</hi> nor <hi>flatteries withdraw</hi> him from <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>ſink</hi> his Spirit. One would wonder <hi>what kind of man Jeſhua</hi> was that hears him ſo <hi>often charged</hi> to be <hi>couragious. Be ſtrong, and</hi> of a good courage, (ſaith God) <hi>for unto this people ſhalt thou divide for an inheritance the Land,</hi> Joſh. 1.6. <hi>Have not I commanded thee?</hi> (ſaith God <hi>again</hi>) <hi>be ſtrong,</hi> and of a good courage, <hi>be not afraid, neither be thou diſmaid</hi> verſe 9. <hi>All that thou commandeſt us</hi> (ſay the <hi>people</hi>) <hi>we will doe, onely be ſtrong, and</hi> of a good courage verſe 18. Not that he was either a <hi>Coward,</hi> for want of <hi>valour,</hi> or <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>flexible</hi> for want of <hi>reſolution:</hi> but having to deal with a <hi>ſtubborn</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, it was neceſſary to <hi>whet</hi> and ſet an <hi>edge</hi> upon his <hi>courage,</hi> for <hi>preparing</hi> him againſt all <hi>trials.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, there is no <hi>perſon</hi> in <hi>Authority,</hi> but he muſt expect to <hi>grapple</hi> with ſome <hi>hardſhip,</hi> to <hi>meet</hi> with ſome <hi>ſevere encounters,</hi> and perhaps when he <hi>doth beſt</hi> to <hi>hear worſt:</hi> nor is there any thing to <hi>buoy</hi> him up, and bring him <hi>ſafely</hi> off, but <hi>arming</hi> himſelf <hi>beforehand,</hi> with a <hi>ſerious reſolve</hi> that nothing ſhall
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:37590:47"/>be of <hi>force</hi> to <hi>move</hi> him out of the <hi>wayes of God.</hi> This therefore God <hi>expects</hi> from <hi>you</hi> in order to the <hi>ſerving your Generation,</hi> that you <hi>valiantly maintain</hi> his <hi>truth,</hi> and when any thing comes in <hi>conteſt</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> that you <hi>ſhrink</hi> not from him, nor <hi>turn</hi> to the <hi>right hand</hi> or to the <hi>left.</hi> It is not for you to <hi>ſwim</hi> with the <hi>ſtream,</hi> but to <hi>ſtrike againſt</hi> it, be it never ſo <hi>fierce;</hi> and if you cannot <hi>beat ſin down,</hi> yet at leaſt to <hi>keep</hi> from the <hi>infection</hi> of it; to <hi>determine</hi> as <hi>Joſhua</hi> did when he took his <hi>farewel</hi> of <hi>Iſrael: If it ſeem evil unto you to ſerve the Lord, chuſe you this day whom you will ſerve: But as</hi> for me and my houſe, <hi>we will ſerve the Lord,</hi> Joſh. 24.15. And that leads me to the <hi>next</hi> Particular.</p>
                  <p>David <hi>ſerved his Generation,</hi> and <hi>by an exemplary life and converſation.</hi> Which was ſo <hi>great</hi> a <hi>part</hi> of his <hi>ſervice,</hi> that our <hi>Engliſh Annotators</hi> have made an <hi>eſpecial remarke</hi> upon it: and thus give the <hi>ſence</hi> of my Text, <hi>after</hi> David <hi>had lived</hi> uprightly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, <hi>in his appointed times he died.</hi> Indeed ſo <hi>exact</hi> was his <hi>walking,</hi> that all the <hi>good Kings</hi> after him are ſaid to <hi>walk in his wayes,</hi> or to <hi>doe as he did.</hi> Of <hi>Joſiah</hi> we read <hi>he did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord, and walked in all the wayes of</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid <hi>his Father,</hi> 2 Kings 22.2. and of <hi>Hezekiah, he did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord, according to all that</hi> David <hi>his Father did,</hi> 2 Kings 18.3. And the <hi>wicked Princes</hi> are ſaid <hi>not to walk in his wayes,</hi> or to <hi>do like him.</hi> So we read of <hi>Abijam, his heart was not perfect with the Lord, as the heart of</hi> David <hi>his Father,</hi> 1 Kings 15.3. The truth is he was a <hi>man,</hi> though not without <hi>infirmities,</hi> yet of a <hi>moſt excellent life;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called the <hi>man after Gods own heart,</hi> Acts 13.22. And the <hi>Character</hi> of him is, <hi>He did that which was right in the eyes of the Lord, and turned not aſide
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:37590:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>from any thing that he commanded him, all the dayes of his life, ſave onely in the matter of</hi> Uriah <hi>the</hi> Hit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, 1 Kings 15.5. And truly this is an <hi>eminent part</hi> of your <hi>duty</hi> in <hi>ſerving your Generation:</hi> and that which will have a very great <hi>influence</hi> upon <hi>all</hi> about you. Believe it there will be <hi>many eyes</hi> upon you; <hi>ſome</hi> out of a <hi>good, ſome</hi> out of a <hi>bad intent; ſome</hi> out of <hi>love, ſome</hi> out of <hi>envy:</hi> And every <hi>ſlip</hi> in you will be ſo much the <hi>greater,</hi> as your <hi>place</hi> is higher: for <hi>he</hi> that enters upon a <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Office, puts off</hi> the <hi>man,</hi> and <hi>puts on</hi> the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</hi> Nor is there a <hi>likelier way</hi> to make <hi>others good</hi> than <hi>your being</hi> ſo. <hi>Philoſophers</hi> tell us that the <hi>inferiour orbes are carried about by the motion of the</hi> primum mobile. And we know the <hi>Proverb, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis ad exemplum,</hi> &amp;c. 'T s true of a <hi>Borough</hi> or <hi>Town,</hi> as well as of a <hi>Kingdome, ſuch</hi> as the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> are, <hi>ſuch</hi> will the <hi>people</hi> be. We ſee it in the caſe of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> While <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>thoſe</hi> with him, who were <hi>exemplary</hi> for <hi>piety</hi> lived, the <hi>people</hi> was <hi>pious</hi> too: Iſrael <hi>ſerved the Lord all the dayes of</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua, <hi>and all the dayes of the Elders that outlived</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua, Joſhua 24.31. And you cannot <hi>at preſent</hi> imagine what a <hi>comfortable reflexion</hi> it will be <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after,</hi> that by your <hi>good converſation,</hi> during the time of your <hi>employment,</hi> you have <hi>contributed</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>promotion</hi> of <hi>piety</hi> and <hi>holineſs.</hi> In ſhort, <hi>men advanced to more than ordinary height, moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly prove either Stars or Comets, and either enlighten or infect our lower World.</hi> For we are moſt what <hi>led</hi> by <hi>practice, praecepta docent, exempla trabunt; precepts inſtruct</hi> us, but <hi>precedents</hi> more <hi>forcibly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliue</hi> us: and as a <hi>Divine</hi> of our own expreſſeth it <hi>wittily, though the words of the wiſe be as nails faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:37590:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>by the Maſters of Aſſemblies,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Fullers</hi> Holy State in the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a good Parent.</note> yet Examples are the Hammers to drive them in, that they may take the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter hold.</hi> You ſee then briefly, wherein <hi>David did,</hi> and <hi>conformably</hi> to <hi>him,</hi> wherein every <hi>good Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate</hi> ſhould <hi>ſerve his Generation. Four</hi> things I have mentioned as <hi>points of duty,</hi> let me adde <hi>four</hi> more as <hi>grounds of encouragement</hi> to theſe <hi>duries;</hi> and they are theſe. The <hi>ſerving your Generation</hi> on this manner will 1. Make <hi>your life honourable:</hi> 2. It will make <hi>your memory precious:</hi> 3. It will make <hi>your people happy:</hi> And 4. It will make <hi>your death comfortable:</hi> All which you ſhall ſee <hi>exactly proved</hi> in <hi>David</hi> himſelf.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>It will make your life Honourable.</hi> A <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> never <hi>acts</hi> with more <hi>policy</hi> for <hi>himſelf,</hi> than when he <hi>acts</hi> with the moſt <hi>piety</hi> towards <hi>God;</hi> Nor can he <hi>deviſe</hi> a readier way to <hi>compaſs</hi> his <hi>own honour,</hi> than by <hi>deſigning</hi> the <hi>honour</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> I <hi>appeal</hi> to the <hi>perſon</hi> in the <hi>Text,</hi> Pſal. 89.27. <hi>I will make him my firſt-born, higher than the Kings of the earth.</hi> So much <hi>more honourable</hi> than all <hi>others</hi> as the <hi>firſt-born</hi> is above his <hi>brethren:</hi> that the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> about him ſhall <hi>ſtoop</hi> to him as one of a <hi>more raiſed dignity</hi> and <hi>renown.</hi> Nor was it only <hi>ſo</hi> in <hi>his</hi> time, but in <hi>Solomons</hi> too. So well was God <hi>pleaſed</hi> with his <hi>requeſt</hi> for <hi>a wiſe and underſtanding heart, that he might diſcern between good and bad;</hi> that he <hi>grants</hi> what he had <hi>aſked,</hi> and <hi>gives</hi> what he <hi>asked not:</hi> both <hi>riches and honour, ſo that there ſhall not</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>be any of the Kings like unto thee, all thy dayes,</hi> 1 Kings 3.13. It is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to produce <hi>more inſtances.</hi> Doe you <hi>your part,</hi> and be ſure <hi>God</hi> will <hi>doe His.</hi> He who <hi>diſtributes</hi> his <hi>judgements</hi> by a <hi>tantum</hi> and <hi>quantum, diſtributes</hi> his <hi>rewards</hi> ſo too: And if you expect a <hi>greater
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:37590:49"/>meaſure</hi> of <hi>honour,</hi> God will expect a <hi>greater meaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e</hi> of <hi>duty.</hi> This is the way to <hi>raiſe</hi> your <hi>Names,</hi> to <hi>advance</hi> your <hi>fame</hi> far above that <hi>parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Nobility</hi> (as <hi>Charron</hi> calls it) which conſiſts onely in <hi>purchaſed titles,</hi> without the <hi>ſupplement</hi> of <hi>vertuous actions.</hi> In a word, <hi>God</hi> will <hi>honour</hi> you, <hi>good men</hi> will <hi>honour</hi> you, and for the <hi>wicked</hi> it is <hi>no matter</hi> whether they <hi>doe</hi> or <hi>not:</hi> though ſhould they <hi>malice,</hi> and <hi>intend miſchief</hi> againſt you, it lies not in their <hi>power</hi> to <hi>hurt</hi> you: for <hi>when a mans wayes pleaſe the Lord, he maketh even his enemies to be at peace with him,</hi> Prov. 16.7.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>It will make your memory precious.</hi> Your <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> ſhall <hi>not die</hi> when <hi>you die,</hi> but <hi>live</hi> many <hi>years,</hi> many <hi>Ages</hi> after you. I need no more <hi>particular proof</hi> of this in the caſe of <hi>David,</hi> than the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving</hi> his <hi>Name,</hi> and that <hi>excellent Encomium</hi> of him <hi>conveyed</hi> in the <hi>Bible</hi> to <hi>ſucceeding Ages,</hi> there to <hi>continue</hi> while the <hi>World endures:</hi> that the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ions</hi> after him might <hi>ſee, ſuch a man</hi> there <hi>was, ſuch a life</hi> he <hi>led,</hi> and <hi>ſuch a memorial</hi> he <hi>left behind</hi> him. So that methinks this <hi>Divine providence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> upon, and <hi>confirms</hi> what he <hi>wrote</hi> by <hi>Divine inſpiration,</hi> Pſal. 112.6. <hi>The righteous ſhall be in ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting remembrance.</hi> Nor was it happineſs <hi>ſingly.</hi> We read that when <hi>Moſes</hi> dyed, God himſelf took care to <hi>bury</hi> him <hi>privately,</hi> Deut. 34.6. <hi>He buried him in a Valley in the land of</hi> Moab, <hi>over againſt</hi> Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peon; <hi>but no man knoweth of his Sepulchre unto this day.</hi> And the <hi>Rabbins</hi> give this <hi>reaſon</hi> of it, <hi>leſt the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>who had ſo great a reverence for his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, ſhould have idolized his Grave,</hi> had they <hi>known</hi> where it was. Moſt certainly <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>fame</hi> reached much <hi>further</hi> than his <hi>own time,</hi> by that
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:37590:49"/>
                     <hi>Character</hi> given him in <hi>after-ages:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>That excellent Law-giver of the</hi> Jews, <hi>and more than a man.</hi> And indeed,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 149.9.</note> 
                     <hi>This honour have all his Saints.</hi> If <hi>you carry</hi> your ſelves in your <hi>places</hi> with the ſame <hi>faithfulneſs</hi> as <hi>they</hi> did, the very <hi>remembrance</hi> of you ſhall be <hi>grateful</hi> to thoſe that <hi>come after</hi> you; and your <hi>vertuous actions</hi> will <hi>preſerve</hi> you <hi>longer</hi> in <hi>memory,</hi> than any <hi>Epitaph</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your <hi>Grave-ſtones.</hi> I leave it to your own <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding,</hi> whether a <hi>commendation written</hi> in the <hi>hearts</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> be not much <hi>more durable</hi> than in <hi>pillars</hi> of <hi>marble:</hi> And who may more <hi>juſtly expect,</hi> or more <hi>rationally hope</hi> for it, than <hi>he</hi> that <hi>diſchargeth</hi> a <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick truſt religiouſly, faithfully, conſcientiouſly?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>This will make your people happy.</hi> (I call them <hi>yours,</hi> whilſt under <hi>your Government</hi>) <hi>Magiſtrates actions</hi> reach further than their <hi>own perſons:</hi> and <hi>tend</hi> extreamly either to the <hi>advantage</hi> or <hi>diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage</hi> of the <hi>places</hi> where they <hi>live.</hi> We ſee it in the caſe of <hi>David:</hi> (for I ſtill <hi>keep</hi> him in mine <hi>eye</hi>) Whilſt he <hi>lived,</hi> Iſrael <hi>flouriſhed</hi> in times of <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>conquered</hi> in times of <hi>war.</hi> Nay, when he was <hi>dead,</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>fared</hi> the <hi>better</hi> for <hi>him. Sennacherib</hi> invades <hi>Judah</hi> ſome 300 <hi>years</hi> after <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> time; <hi>Ahaz</hi> had <hi>provoked</hi> God to <hi>anger</hi> by his <hi>Idolatry,</hi> yet notwithſtanding that <hi>provocation,</hi> God <hi>thinks</hi> of <hi>David, remembers</hi> his <hi>piety,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves <hi>for his ſake, Jeruſalem</hi> ſhould be <hi>defended: I will defend this City to ſave it, for mine own ſake, and for my ſervant</hi> Davids <hi>ſake;</hi> 2 Kings 19.34. And truly this is but what <hi>elſewhere</hi> we <hi>learn</hi> from the <hi>Scripture,</hi> Prov. 28.2. <hi>For the tranſgreſſion of a land many are the Princes thereof, but by a man of underſtanding the ſtate thereof ſhall be prolonged:</hi> it
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:37590:50"/>ſhall be made <hi>healthfull,</hi> as <hi>health</hi> is a great means of <hi>prolonging life.</hi> And I know not well how to uſe a <hi>ſtronger Motive.</hi> What <hi>greater comfort</hi> hath the <hi>Nurſe</hi> than to ſee the <hi>Child thrive</hi> at her <hi>breaſt?</hi> And what <hi>greater ſatisfaction</hi> to a <hi>good Governour,</hi> than to ſee the <hi>Town happy</hi> under his <hi>Government,</hi> nay to <hi>lay</hi> a <hi>foundation</hi> (as much as can be) to <hi>perpetuate</hi> its <hi>happineſs</hi> many <hi>years after</hi> him? Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me if I <hi>urge</hi> this with ſome <hi>earneſtneſs,</hi> out of the <hi>honour</hi> I <hi>bear</hi> to this <hi>place. May all the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of heaven continually reſt, and the tender mercies of the moſt High deſcend upon it. May all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants find Grace, Plenty, and Peace; and the Town flouriſh while the Sun and Moon endure.</hi> To which <hi>Petitions God Almighty</hi> ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>This will make your death comfortable. Death</hi> makes no <hi>difference</hi> between <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> between <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Peaſant.</hi> The <hi>Mortall Sythe</hi> is <hi>Maſter</hi> of the <hi>Royall Scepter,</hi> and <hi>mowes</hi> down the <hi>Lillies</hi> of the <hi>Crown,</hi> as well as the <hi>Graſs</hi> of the <hi>Field. Die</hi> you <hi>muſt,</hi> be you never ſo <hi>great,</hi> be you never ſo <hi>vertuous:</hi> only your <hi>vertue</hi> will be a <hi>good preſervative</hi> againſt the <hi>terrors</hi> of <hi>death,</hi> and will <hi>cheer</hi> up your <hi>hearts</hi> in the <hi>deepeſt Agony. Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin</hi> (I remember) <hi>compares</hi> it to the <hi>Geometricall Cube,
<note n="*" place="margin">Holy Court, in the life of <hi>Theodoſius.</hi>
                        </note> caſt it on what ſide you will, it always finds its Baſis.</hi> Whether we <hi>live</hi> or <hi>die,</hi> it <hi>affords</hi> us <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> when <hi>nothing elſe</hi> in the world can <hi>do</hi> it. With what <hi>Tranquillity</hi> did <hi>David go to his Father?</hi> When he had <hi>done</hi> his <hi>work</hi> he <hi>lies down</hi> in <hi>peace</hi> to <hi>take</hi> his <hi>reſt;</hi> whereupon his <hi>death</hi> is called a <hi>falling on ſleep. David after he had ſerved his own Generation by the will of God, fell on ſleep;</hi> which is the <hi>ſecond</hi> part of the <hi>text:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:37590:50"/>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Davids reſt: he fell on ſleep.</hi> A <hi>Metaphoricall</hi> word, though very <hi>appoſite</hi> and <hi>ſignificant. Sleep</hi> is a <hi>ſhort death; Death</hi> is a <hi>long ſleep:</hi> when the <hi>earth</hi> is our <hi>bed,</hi> a <hi>winding-ſheet</hi> our <hi>cloths,</hi> the great <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection-day</hi> our <hi>morning</hi> to <hi>awake</hi> in, and the <hi>Arch-Angels Trumpet</hi> our <hi>Monitor</hi> to <hi>ariſe.</hi> It is a <hi>ſleep</hi> for its <hi>refreſhment.</hi> A <hi>nights reſt recruits</hi> that <hi>ſtrength</hi> which was <hi>ſpent</hi> in the <hi>days toil:</hi> and our <hi>bodies</hi> ſhall be <hi>raiſed</hi> in a far <hi>better plight</hi> than we <hi>laid</hi> them <hi>down.</hi> For this <hi>corruptible muſt put on incorruption, and this mortall muſt put on immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> 1 Cor. 15.53. But I <hi>dare</hi> not proſecute this <hi>Paralell</hi> any further. Let me therefore <hi>entreat</hi> you as you <hi>expect comfort</hi> when all <hi>earthly Comforts for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake</hi> you; as you <hi>value Peace of Conſcience</hi> at your <hi>laſt hour;</hi> and a <hi>pleaſant paſſage</hi> into <hi>eternity:</hi> as you would have the <hi>King of terrors preſented</hi> leſs <hi>dreadfull,</hi> and be <hi>ready</hi> to <hi>give up your accounts</hi> with <hi>joy: See</hi> to what I have <hi>charged</hi> as your <hi>duties.</hi> And <hi>think</hi> but with your ſelves how it will <hi>revive</hi> your <hi>ſpirits</hi> to <hi>ſay</hi> with the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> 2 Cor. 1.12. <hi>Our rejoycing is this, the teſtimony of our Conſcience, that in all ſimplicity and godly ſincerity, we have had our converſation in the world.</hi> How <hi>merrily</hi> you may <hi>ſing</hi> a <hi>Nunc dimittis, Lord now letteſt thou thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant depart in peace,</hi> when you can <hi>appeal</hi> to <hi>God</hi> both as <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> with <hi>good Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> Iſai. 38.3. <hi>Remember O Lord how I have walked before thee, in truth, and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is right in thy ſight.</hi> To ſhut up all: <hi>Remember who</hi> it is that <hi>ſets</hi> you in your <hi>ſtation, what</hi> he requires from you, that you are but <hi>Servants,</hi> and as <hi>Servants</hi> muſt be <hi>accountable:</hi> that a <hi>time</hi> is <hi>coming</hi> for your <hi>appearance</hi> before the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:37590:51"/>great <hi>Tribunall,</hi> where you ſhall be <hi>queſtioned</hi> for the <hi>management</hi> of <hi>all</hi> your <hi>offices.</hi> Let theſe things <hi>ſink</hi> into your hearts, and <hi>direct</hi> you in your <hi>actions;</hi> that <hi>doing Davids work, ſerving your Generations by the will of God,</hi> you may <hi>enter</hi> into <hi>Davids reſt.</hi> your <hi>bodies</hi> may <hi>reſt</hi> ſecurely in the <hi>grave,</hi> and your <hi>ſouls</hi> enjoy that <hi>eternall reſt which remains to the people of God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 4.9.</note> To which <hi>reſt</hi> God of his mercy <hi>bring</hi> us <hi>all</hi> through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> To whom with the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> be <hi>Honour, Praiſe, Power, Dominions</hi> and <hi>Thanksgiving,</hi> now henceforth, and for evermore. Amen.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:37590:51"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Authors abſence from</hi> London <hi>hath occaſioned ſome miſtakes, eſpecially in the two firſt ſheets of this Book. Such as are leſs material, whether miſ-pointing, or miſ-placing of Marginal Quotations, the Reader is deſired courteouſly to pardon: Such as are of greater concernment be theſe following, which be may correct with his Pen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PAge 7. line. 25. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 10. l. 11. for <hi>from</hi> r. <hi>for.</hi> p. 11. l. 1. for <hi>Reepers</hi> r. <hi>Keepers.</hi> l. 15. r. <hi>legible.</hi> l. 32. for <hi>thy</hi> r. <hi>they.</hi> p. 12. l. 32. for <hi>riches</hi> r. <hi>wiſhes.</hi> l. ult. for <hi>took</hi> r. <hi>take.</hi> p. 13. l. 26. for <hi>preferred</hi> r. <hi>preſerved.</hi> p. 15. l. 29. for <hi>gentle</hi> r. <hi>gentile.</hi> p. 18. l. 7. for <hi>thou</hi> r. <hi>then.</hi> p. 19. l. 12. for <hi>Goals</hi> r. <hi>Gaols</hi> twice. p. 23. l. 8. for <hi>and</hi> r. <hi>not.</hi> p. 25. l. 23. for 12. r. 122. p. 27. l. 20. marg. r. <hi>Vicars.</hi> p. 28. l. 17. for <hi>Son</hi> r. <hi>Sun.</hi> l. 22. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. l. 30. for <hi>Elion</hi> r. <hi>Ebion.</hi> p. 29. l. 15. after <hi>totus</hi> adde <hi>mundus.</hi> p. 38. l. 3. r. <hi>releaſe.</hi> p. 56. l. 9. for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 62. l. 22. for <hi>our</hi> r. <hi>your.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
